find
finden
Ask
Ask
I would like to welcome everyone to participate today
今天要歡迎大家來參加
we tonight
我們今天晚上
Speech at the Knowledge Feast of the Institute of Public Studies
眾研院知識饗宴的演講
Everyone has seen the title of our speech today
大家都看到我們今天的演講的題目
First of all, I would like to introduce our speaker today
首先我要介紹我們今天的演講人
The protagonist is our Dr. Xu Wenlian
主角人是我們的許文蓮博士
The current Institute of Information Science
現任資訊科學研究所的
Special researcher and director
特品研究員兼所長
Director Xu was in 1973
許所長是在1973年
Graduated from National Taiwan University Department of Mathematics
從台大數學系畢業
in 1979
在1979年
Cornell University
取得美國康奈爾大學的
He is a Ph.D. in Operational Studies
他是在作業研究的博士學位
Because it is Operation Research
因為是Operation Research
in 1980
1980年
Taught at Northwestern University
在美國西北大學任教
Got a permanent offer
拿到了永久聘書
but probably feel
可是大概覺得
Should be returning home to serve
應該是要回國服務
So in 1989 when
所以在1989年的時候
back to
回到
Academia Sinica Information Service
中央研究院資訊所服務
Now the director of the Information Office
現在是資訊所的所長
When Professor Xu was at Northwestern University in his early days
許教授早期在西北大學的時候
His research focuses on
他的研究是偏重於
The Theory of Mindful Algorithm
徒心演算法的理論
His two papers on planar perfect graphs
他在平面完美圖上的兩篇論文
is a classic in this field
是這個領域的經典之作
He is also working in computational biology
同時他也在計算生物學
In the analysis and alignment of DNA sequences
在DNA的序列的分析比對上
Many error-dissolving algorithms have been designed
設計了很多溶錯演算法
According to the series of proteins
根據蛋白質的系列進行
Prediction of function and structure
功能與結構的預測
Analysis of Hezhipuyi Therapeutic Medicine
跟植普以治藥的分析
after he returns home
他回國以後
Continuing research on these theoretical aspects
繼續在這些理論方面的研究
Then also take the experience of these algorithms
然後同時也把這些演算法的經驗
Applied in Chinese natural language research
運用在中文自然語言研究
and system development
及的系統發展
Then developed the intelligent
然後發展了智慧型的
Make sound input method
做音輸入法
So in 1993 published the state-run input method
所以在1993年發表國營輸入法
Won the first Top Ten Outstanding Chinese Information Products Award
獲得了第一屆十大傑出中文資訊產品獎
Then published the natural input method in 1995
然後在1995年發表了自然輸入法
These experiences of subsequent artificial intelligence research
其後這些人工智慧研究的這些經驗
Also applied to the Internet for Chinese question answering system
也應用到網際網路進行中文問答系統
So with robotics research
所以與機器人的研究
So we might hear something about that today
所以我們今天可能會聽到一些這方面的東西
These studies have implications for building large-scale language application systems in industry
這些研究對工業界建立大型語言應用系統
For example, online customer service
譬如說網路客服
Sentiment analysis of Q&A opinions within the enterprise
企業內部的問答意見情緒分析
Or product recommendations, etc. are very suitable
或商品推薦等等都非常的合適
Professor Xu's outstanding research
許教授這些傑出的研究
He has received three National Science Council Distinguished Awards
他得到了三次國科會的傑出獎
Then won the first Li Guoding Chuanshi Award
然後得過第一屆李國鼎川石獎
There is also the American IEEE
還有美國IEEE
is a meeting of an association
是一個協會的會事
There are many awards from the Pan Wenyuan Research Association for the Central Plains Award
中原獎有很多潘文淵研究協出獎
2012 Information Medal of Honor from the Information Society of the Republic of China
中華民國資訊學會的2012年的資訊榮譽獎章
So in addition to his cognition in the Central Plains Academy
所以他除了在中原院認知之外
Also served as the chairman of the Republic of China Society for Artificial Intelligence
也擔任過中華民國人工智慧學會的理事長
and the chairman of the Institute of Computational Linguistics, etc.
以及計算語言學會理事長等等
Say a lot about service experience
說很多服務的經驗
Has a track record of award-winning research
有很多研究上的一些得獎的紀錄
So our Knowledge Award Academy hopes to say
所以我們這個知識獎院希望是說
Introduce to everyone the comparatively contacted research in the Central Plains Institute
把中原院裡面比較接觸的研究介紹給大家
Then I hope to be able to say in a more common language
然後希望能夠說用一個比較通俗的語言
Introduce to the public what we are doing with this research
介紹給大眾說這個研究我們在做些什麼事情
So today we see that the topic of this speech is about
那今天的我們看這個演講的題目是關於
The field of artificial intelligence is probably
人工智慧這個領域是在大概
A field that was only founded 60 years ago
60年前才成立的一個領域
You can see that it has largely fallen in the past 60 years
大家可以看到說它是在60年間曾經大體大落
just nerves are very hot
就是神經非常熱門
Then there was a period of time when the development was slower
然後有一段時間發展比較慢一點
But recently because of deep learning
可是最近因為深度學習
So in this area it's re-emphasizing
所以在這個領域又重新設到重視
So we are talking about Artificial Intelligence in this
所以我們在這個對於說 Artificial Intelligence
artificial intelligence
人工智慧這方面
There have been many other recent developments related to
最近又有很多其他有關的一些發展
It makes everyone in the academic world have some new perceptions of this field
使得大家學術界對這個領域又有一些新的觀感
We also saw in the newspaper recently that there is Google's Appagope
我們在報紙上也看到最近說有 Google 的 Appagope
We put Weiqi some national players
是我們把微奇的一些國手
The world's masters are all defeated
世界高手就全部打敗了
So it is to use a concept of deep learning
所以是利用一個深度的學習的概念
Only then did such great results be achieved
然後才達成這樣子的很大的成果
So let's start now by saying we want to be able to
所以說我們現在開始說希望能夠
To predict when we can use these
預測什麼時候我們可以用這些
APAGO's Language Prediction System
APAGO的語言預測系統
understand the system
理解系統
So in this speech
所以在這次演講上
we'll see some introduction to this
我們就會看到一些這方面的介紹
So natural language understanding
所以自然語言理解
Is the last level of artificial intelligence
是人工智慧的最後關卡
So I think Xu Shuochang is right about this topic
所以我想許說長對這個題目
I won't say more
我就不再多說
We will listen to Xu Shuochang's speech
我們會聽聽許說長的演講
see what is called
看看說什麼叫做
The final hurdle of artificial intelligence
人工智慧的最後關卡
so we now
所以我們現在
I hope everyone with the warmest applause
希望大家以最熱烈的掌聲
Come and welcome our host today
來歡迎我們今天的主持人
Introduction by Vice President Zhou
周副院長的介紹
Thank you all for coming
也謝謝各位來參加
I have this opportunity to share with you
有這個機會跟大家分享一下
So many years of research
這這麼多年研究
i remember ten years ago
我記得在十年前
I also talked about the feast of knowledge here, and I also talked about artificial intelligence
我也在這裡講過知識饗宴,也是講人工智慧
But the progress of the past ten years is actually very dramatic
但這十年進步其實是非常的dramatic
So I would like to share my personal research experience on language
所以我大概分享一下我個人在語言上面的這些研究的心得
This research will actually have a great impact on everyone, especially young people
這個研究其實會對各位,尤其對年輕的人影響會很大
Because in the future, if the ability of computers to understand natural language increases, many jobs will disappear
因為未來如果電腦對自然語言理解能力增加的話,很多工作都會消失
We can now see that Hon Hai claims to have an army of 40 million in the mainland, and tens of thousands of them are robots
我們現在看到,鴻海在大陸號稱四十百萬大軍,裡面有多少萬都是機器人
His entire factory is now called a factory without lights, and there is no need to turn on the lights at all.
他現在整個工廠是叫無燈工廠,根本不需要開燈的
can get things done from start to finish
就可以把事情從頭到尾做好
So in the future when the white-collar class handles paperwork in the office, the computer can help you write and read letters
所以以後在白領階級在辦公室處理文書,電腦可以幫你寫信,可以幫你讀信
Of course, that level is relatively shallow, but he can do a lot of secretarial things
當然那個level是比較淺一點,但是比較秘書方面的事情很多他都可以做
This is a future one, it will happen within five years
這個是一個未來的一個,大概在五年之內就會發生
So I now name this as the final level of artificial intelligence
所以我現在把這個名字定成人工智慧的最後關卡
Because everyone knows that computers have also made rapid progress in vision recently.
因為各位大家知道最近電腦在視覺上面也進步很快
Can tell cats and dogs apart which means it doesn't need much of these people's intervention
可以分辨出貓狗就是說它不需要太多的這些人的介入
it can be done
它就可以做到
But it's far from there
但這方面還差很遠
Speech is progressing rapidly
語音方面進步很快
Now everyone has used Google's audiobook
現在各位用過Google的語音書
or Siri's voicebook is known to be very accurate
或Siri的語音書都知道它的準確度非常高
It's just that it doesn't understand
只是差在它並不了解
In most cases it just uses other technologies to correct the speech
大部分情況它只是用別的技術把語音辨對
but it doesn't understand what you're talking about
但是它不了解你在講什麼
So let's take a look today
所以我們今天來看一下
This is to understand what you are talking about
這個要了解各位在說什麼
how difficult is this
這個有多困難
So my Daeko is like this today
所以我今天大光是這樣
I'll start with a simple personal brevity
我先做一個簡單的個人簡潔
then artificial intelligence
然後是人工智慧
natural language understanding
再來自然語言理解
The last thing is to say which jobs will be replaced by computers
最後才是說哪一些工作會被電腦取代
personally
我個人方面
Since I was a child, I prefer to use my brain rather than my hands.
從小是比較喜歡動腦不喜歡動手
i often think
我常常在想
At that time, of course
那個時候當然就是說
All of our environments are very
我們所有的環境都非常的
Very difficult to do a lot of automated things
非常查不容易做很多自動化的事情
I'm studying mathematics in college and it's a good training
我大學在讀數學是一個很好的訓練
Because I find the theories that are the most difficult to say
因為我覺得說最困難的那些理論
Probably we've all been through it and don't necessarily say it's a good read
大概我們都經過不見得說讀得很好
But we at least after
但我們至少經過以後
go to other fields
轉到其他領域
No threshold does not mean easy
沒有門檻並不是說容易
It means that your mathematics is basically fearless
而是說你的數學基本上沒有畏懼感
Well, it's actually not easy for many people.
那這對很多人講其實這不容易
So early artificial intelligence
所以早期人工智慧
is proved by logic and theorem
是被邏輯和定理證明
The earliest artificial intelligence actually has very few systems
最早人工智慧事實上系統很少
because then you know
因為那時候各位知道
Computers are really underpowered
電腦實在是非常的能力不足
When I was studying at National Taiwan University
我在讀台大的時候
whole school
整個學
What is the memory of the computer in National Taiwan University?
台灣大學電腦的記憶體是多少
Can you guess it?
各位可以猜出來嗎
Now we may be 16GB
現在我們可能是16GB
that is 16K
那個是16K
Not 16K sorry
不是16K 抱歉
16GB
16GB
Just 16GB can't do anything at all
就是16GB 根本就不能做什麼事情
So I used to do theory
所以以前都是做理論
Do theory
做理論的話
Syneron Puffing is the automatic proof of theorem
Syneron Puffing就是定理自動證明
This was very popular before
這個是以前滿流行的
There is a famous professor in our country
我們國內有一位很有名的教授
in doing this
在做這一方面
very old professor
年紀很大的教授
Do you know who it is?
各位知道是誰嗎
very famous
很有名
Professor Li Jiatong
李家彤教授
he doesn't mention it now
他現在都不提
Because he did it then and later he
因為他那時候做到後來他
I think he kind of hates the field
我覺得他有點恨這個領域
He thinks that automatic proof is too difficult
他覺得那個自動證明太難了
So in the future, he will treat people who do AI
所以他以後就對做AI的人
a little disgusted
有一點的反感
Thanks
謝謝
At that time, AI academics talked more and did less
那個時候 AI 學者說得多做得少
this is impossible
這個是沒有辦法的事情
Because the computer age was very slow at that time
因為電腦時代那個時候是非常慢
We should have written this 30 years ago
我們這應該寫30年前
I made a mistake in the constant number 30 years ago
我寫錯了 30年前中恆數
I went there in 1980 when I was teaching at Northwestern University
我在西北大學教宿的時候是1980 去的
In 1982, I saw the first Datong green screen
1982年我就看到第一台大同的綠色的螢幕
If you're old enough to know
如果各位年紀夠大的話就知道
The first generation of IPM computers
第一代的 IPM 的電腦
The hardware is almost all made by Datong
硬體幾乎都是大同做的
So its little screen is a green
所以它那個小螢幕是一個綠色
Appeared in 1982
1982年出現
This caused a great shock in Western countries
這個在西方國家引起一個很大的震撼
Almost all typewriters disappeared within half a year
幾乎在半年之內所有的打字機幾乎都消失了
I used to use electric typewriters
以前都是用電動打字機
Later, it was all replaced by computer screens.
後來全部換成電腦螢幕
Even kindergarten kids can play by themselves
連幼稚園的小孩他都可以自己打
So this is a very natural thing in pinyin countries
所以這個在拼音國家是非常自然的事情
Because it only has 26 keys and 26 subtitles, it can type out all languages
因為它只有26個鍵26個字幕就可以把所有語言打出來
But Chinese is extremely difficult
可是在中文上面困難度高得不得了
At that time, professional typing companies were using the Changjie input method.
那時候都是專業打字公司在用昌傑輸入法
Now you may rarely hear that you have to recite those Changjie horses.
現在各位可能很少聽到要去背那些昌傑馬什麼的
Changjie input method
昌傑輸入法
The Zhuyin input method was immature at that time
注音輸入法那時候還不成熟
is very high error rate
就是錯誤率非常高
Therefore, we hope to develop automatic phonetic selection input in foreign countries.
所以我們在國外就很希望能夠發展自動選擇注音輸入
We often compare a person who can't type Chinese
我們常常比喻一個不會打中文輸入的
It's a foreigner on a computer
就是在電腦上的外國人
That is, he still needs translation when facing the computer
就是他面對電腦還需要翻譯
At that time, we had many teachers who received
我們那時候有很多老師他受到
Both English and English can be typed
英文是英文都可以打
This wasn’t in 1982, probably when I returned to Taiwan in 1990
這個不是在1982大概到我回台灣所1990
He can type all English letters without any problem.
英文信他都可以打沒有問題了
But as soon as he comes across Chinese, he prints it out
但是一碰到中文他就把它印出來
and write his reply on it
然後在上面寫他的回信
Then ask the secretary to type the reply letter into Chinese and send it out
然後再請秘書把回信打成中文送出去
So earlier
所以比較早期的
Almost all secretaries will participate in the input method
秘書幾乎全部都會參加輸入法
that's why
就是這個原因
I think communicating with the computer is a very important communication
我覺得跟電腦溝通是一個非常重要的communication
If a country is productive
如果一個國家生產力
You can communicate with the computer only when you use English
你只有用英文的時候可以跟電腦交通
Chinese is not good at all
中文完全不行
this is a very poor one
這是非常可憐的一個
So we spent a lot of time doing Chinese
所以我們就花了很多時間在做中文
But the first thing I did was because I needed to type Chinese
但最早做這個是因為自己需要打中文
i saw that jubangful early
我很早就看到那個朱邦富爾
How does he do that reference input method
他怎麼做那個參節輸入法
But I don't want to recite that section
但我是不願意去背那個參節
I have another problem when I fight Zhu Ying
我打朱英的時候還有一個問題
It's the current standard keyboard
就是那個現在的標準鍵盤
is four rows
是四排的
English English playing is three rows
英文 英打是三排
all in the middle
都在中間的
and very
而且非常
It is very convenient
就是手非常方便
So I was
所以我當初
At the beginning, I made this natural input method
當初做這個自然輸入法
One reason is because I don't like using the standard keyboard
一個原因是因為我不喜歡用那個標準鍵盤
I must develop a keyboard of my own
我一定要發展一個自己的鍵盤
So then there was a Xu-style keyboard
所以後來有一個許式鍵盤
then me
那我這個
I'll talk about it later, back to the Central Plains in 1989 with Mr. Chen Kejian
等一下再講,1989年回到中原和陳克健老師
He is a very senior research scholar in our field
他是我們這方面的一個非常senior的一個研究學者
In 1991, an initial heart system was probably established.
那91年大概就建立一個初心系統
Then when we made it in 1991
那我們91年做出來的時候
Probably until the information month of 1992
大概到92年的那個資訊月
We didn't really launch a product until December
12月的時候我們才真的推出一個產品
It was also written by an outside company for me.
也是外面的公司幫我寫
Because we have no idea how to write such a commercial system
因為我們完全不知道怎麼去寫這種商用系統
The system used at that time may not have been heard by most of you
那個時候用的系統可能大部分在座都沒聽過
called DOS
叫DOS
The memory of the entire computer in the DOS system can only control 640K
DOS系統的整個電腦的memory只能控制640K
640K less than a Mega
640K不到一個Mega
Now we have a Mega for every photo
現在我們一張照片隨便一張照片就一個Mega
Its entire computer is 640K
它整個電腦是640K
So you're going to make a sulva, squeeze it in this
所以你要做個sulva,要把它擠在這個裡面
Then all the rules of all the warehouses must be entered.
然後所有持庫什麼規則全部都要進去
very difficult, so the theory I did
非常困難,所以我當初做的理論
This algorithm helps a lot with this
這個演算法對這個幫助很大
So we mourned the name in natural calligraphy in 1990
所以我們1990年用自然書法的名稱喪事
By 1995, Microsoft hoped to be able to license our calligraphy
到95年的時候微軟就希望能夠license我們這個書法
he speaks very well
那他講得很好聽
他說It's your honor to be used by
他說It's your honor to be used by
It is your honor to be placed in Microsoft, right?
就是你放在微軟是你的榮譽對不對
That means I don't really need to give you money.
那意思就是說不太需要給你錢的
not that we want the money
並不是我們要這個錢
We think he probably wouldn't talk to the inventor like that in a foreign country
我們覺得說在國外他大概不會跟那個發明家這樣講
It's a very rude thing in my opinion.
是非常我覺得是非常不禮貌的一件事
so we refuse
所以我們就拒絕
Then we officially approved this funding in 1999 and downloaded it for free
那我們1999年正式在這個批資同免費下載
So it has been the champion of all downloaded software for seven consecutive weeks
所以連續七週都是所有的下載軟體的冠軍
Then my important calligraphy is to say
那我這一個重要的書法就是說
There is a Xu Zhijian card inside
裡面有個許治鍵牌
All those who can type English but not Chinese when they come back from abroad
所有在國外回來會打英文不會打中文的人
It happens to be my training object
正好是我的這個訓練對象
So at that time, Chen Wenchun, the principal of Tsinghua University,
所以那個時候清華校長陳文春
of course i want
我當然我要
Find someone older to teach
要找年紀大一點的人教
He really learned it in about ten minutes.
他大概真的十分鐘就學會了
It's his correspondence with that Zhuyin
就是他跟那個注音的對應
I remember it in ten minutes
完全十分鐘就記起來
There is also an alto director on the TV of the Ministry of Education
另外有個教育部電視上的中音主任
He said using the happy history is a growing professor
他說用了高興史是一個成長的教授
He said I want to help you promote
他說我要幫你推廣
I said you can't help me promote in academia
我說你在學術界沒辦法幫我推廣
that this is actually
那這個其實
transcribe
音轉制
each of us
我們每一個
There are about five to fifteen homophones below Zhuyin
注音下面大概有五到十五個同音制
So you typed out ten words
所以你打了十個字出來
That's a huge number of combinations
那個組合數目不得了
if you don't understand
如果不懂
this
這個
people who don't understand Chinese
不懂中文的人
It's very difficult to spell it out
要去拼出來是非常困難
So now the audio book
所以現在其實語音書
voice book words
語音書的話
one tone below
一個音下面
If you pronounce a sound, there may be
你念一個音可能下面有
there are fifty to one hundred
有五十個到一百個
possible word
可能的字
Because his confusion is high
因為他的混淆度很高
So so many confusing words inside
所以這麼多的混淆的字裡面
To be able to turn him all right
要能夠把他整個轉正確
looks like
看起來是
mission impossible
mission impossible
Now you seem to Google me all at once
你現在Google好像一下就把我全部做回
In fact, there are many tricks in it
其實裡面有很多的trick
So I talk about this current lack of understanding
所以我講這個目前缺乏的理解
It's just that I don't have a trick
就是我沒有一個trick的方法
This system can be made quickly
可以很快把這個系統做出來
let me tell you now
那我現在講一下
You may understand right now
各位可能馬上聽得懂
You put the information on this network
你把這個網路上的資料
Every seven characters are memorized by a window
每七個字一個window背起來
Then memorize the pinyin below it
然後它下面的是什麼拼音背起來
just like this
就這樣一直背背背
After memorizing an article
把一個文章背完了以後
After memorizing about hundreds of thousands of articles
背了大概幾十萬篇以後
The combination of these words and pinyin you memorized
你背的這些字和拼音的組合
take what anyone says
拿去用到任何人講的話
almost what he said
幾乎他講的話
There will be a part in the middle that is the same as this
都會在中間某一部分跟這個是一樣
right away
那馬上就對上去
So don't think Google is great
所以你不要以為Google很了不起
It's actually quite a simple way
其實是相當簡單的一個方式
Then we are also working on the mobile version now
那我們現在也在做手機版
Both Chinese and English are preferred
中英文均可打首選
It is very convenient to type in English
這個打英文是非常方便
You may not remember some English words firmly
各位可能有些英文字記不牢
or it's too much trouble
或者是打起來太麻煩
like we have a biological DNA
像我們有一個生物上的DNA
The word DN is Doxyribonucle
DN這個字叫Doxyribonucle
There are 13 letters
有13個字母
I don't want to go even if I beat you
即使會打你也不願意去
One by one will make a mistake
一個一個打都會打錯
so our
所以我們的
Because our system probably hits 3 or 4 keys
因為我們系統大概打3 4個鍵
just type it out
就可以把它打出來
Let's start with the introduction of artificial intelligence
下面我們開始介紹一下人工智慧
In fact, in my previous profile, I have already put
我前面個人簡介裡面其實已經把
Some of my relationship with artificial intelligence
我跟人工智慧的某些關係
have spoken out
已經講出來
Wait a minute we'll use the example
等一下我們會用這個例子
to explain more artificial intelligence
來解釋更多人工智慧
How artificial intelligence first designed machines to
人工智慧最早是如何設計機器來
simulated intelligence
模擬人的智慧
This is actually very complicated
這個其實講起來複雜度很高
How much do you want to simulate a human
你要模擬人到什麼程度
What we are talking about today is relatively simple
我們今天講的程度是比較簡單的
It is to help human beings solve problems in life and work
是幫人類解決在生活工作中
simple problem encountered
遇到的簡單問題
I don't want to talk about that
我不要去講那個什麼
Their Favorite Philosophers Talk About Conscious
他們最喜歡談的哲學家講Conscious
will he know he exists
他會不會知道他存在
then will he have feelings
然後他會不會有感情
it's all very complicated
這都非常複雜
we are interested in saying
我們有興趣的是說
Assistant-like functions can accept natural language instructions
類似助理功能可以接受自然語言指令
able to do this
能夠做到這件事
Many of our document processing is very simple
我們很多的文書處理就非常簡單
Like I often have problems when using PowerPoint
像我在用PowerPoint的時候常常有問題
i want this
我要把這個
Like some screens are 19%
像有的螢幕是那個19成
169% is relatively wide
16成9是比較寬的
Some screens are 40% to 30%
有的螢幕是4成3
like this is 4 into 3
像這個是4成3
Then I want to turn my slideshow into 16 to 9
那我想把我的投影片變成16成9
if he could understand
如果他會聽得懂
I told him to turn the screen into 16 to 9
我就跟他講把這個螢幕變成16成9
he will soon
他馬上就
If you read his manual
你如果去看他的那個手冊
Indicates how many keys to press
說明要按不到多少鍵
and that no one will know
而且那是沒有人會知道的
So this is a very important
所以這個是一個非常重要的
So how to make software and home appliance manuals answer automatically
所以如何讓軟體和家電使用手冊自動回答
The same goes for home appliances
家電也是一樣
You buy a new cooler now
你現在買一個新的冷機機
right
對不對
Maybe that controller on the old chiller next to it
也許旁邊舊的冷機機那個控制器
already familiar
已經很熟
But new ones have to be learned again
但新的又要重學一次
then what we want is to say
那我們希望的就是說
I told him it's too hot now
我跟他講說現在太熱
It stops after two hours
這個開兩個小時就停
How about turning it off an hour before I go to bed?
我睡覺以前一個小時就關掉了怎麼樣
It doesn't matter what brand you are for this kind of thing
這一類的東西它不管你是哪一家牌子
I don't even need to read the manual if you can understand
你能夠聽得懂的話我根本不需要去看使用手冊
So the ideal in the future is to say that all these manuals disappear
所以以後的這個理想是說這些所有手冊都消失
completely unnecessary
完全不需要
The company's customer service staff don't need to answer questions.
那個公司的客服員也不太需要回答問題
Then the Homepage made by each of us can conduct question and answer
然後我們每一個人做的Homepage就可以進行問答
What does it mean
這是什麼意思呢
Now the Homepage says when and where did you graduate from?
現在Homepage上面有寫什麼時候從哪裡畢業啊
what are you doing?
做什麼事啊什麼對不對
Many people who are looking for a job hope that others can visit his webpage
很多人找工作的人他就希望別人能夠來看他的網頁
This can be a passive one seeing
這個能夠是一個被動式的一個看見
If you want to be proactive
如果說要做主動式的話
People can ask questions on your website
人家可以在你網頁上面問問題
You don't even need to come to your website
甚至你不需要來你網頁
just ask a question say
只要問一個問題說
Which school Xu Wennian graduated from, he can answer right away
許文年哪個學校畢業他馬上就可以回答
So we're spending a lot of money now to make this page
所以我們現在花很多錢去做這個網頁
We're going to pay for this automated answer in the future
以後我們要花錢去做這個自動回答
but this automatic answer
但這個自動回答
yes some packages
是有一些套裝軟體
Just put your knowledge in it now
就馬上把你的知識放進去
it can answer
它就可以回答
It's better that you don't need to spend any more money
這樣最好就不需要再花錢
The following is the IoT
下面就是IoT
It is the devices of the Internet of Things
就是物聯網這些device
able to operate by itself
能夠自行操作
this is very important
這個非常重要
So we talk about smart cities
所以我們講智慧城市
Smart families are talking about
智慧家庭都是在講
A Natural Language Human-Machine Interface
一個自然語言的人機介面
All of these mechanized actions below
下面所有的機械化的這些動作
In fact, its difficulty is relatively low
其實它的難度相對的比較低
The hardest thing is to understand what you want to do
最難的就是聽懂你要幹什麼
So the field of artificial intelligence research
所以人工智慧研究領域
There are the following
有下面這些
Everyone is familiar with this
這大家都很熟
This is image processing
這個是影像處理
Then Graphics
然後是Graphics
Next is the robot
再來是機器人
Then Speed ​​Recognition
然後是Speed Recognition
speech recognition natural language
語音辨識 自然語言
Then give up the whole language
然後捨全語
search engine
搜尋引擎
machine learning
機器學習
Data Mining
Data Mining
biological information
生物資訊
These are all like AI
這些都像是AI的
born of a child
生出來的小孩的
at different times
在不同時間
but a few years ago
但是在幾年前
5 years ago to ask people in these fields
5年前去問這些領域的人
He said I no longer do AI
他說說我不再做AI
why do this
為什麼要這樣
Can you figure it out?
各位想得出來嗎
That is to say, AI used to have a very bad livelihood
就是說AI以前有一個很壞的民生
Just because he gets too many research grants
就他拿得太多研究經費
Especially the funding of the U.S. military
尤其是美國軍方的經費
I don't know how much is invested in AI
不知道多少都投到AI上面
did not get any
結果沒有得到任何的
very little benefit
就非常少的benefit
So to be a scholar of AI
所以做AI的學者
There are many coming and going
來來去去有好多
How many years has it been like this
有多少年都這樣
did not achieve his purpose
沒有達到他的目的
like my wife used to talk about the stuff i made
像我太太常講說我做的東西
He thinks this level is really not high enough
他覺得這個level實在是不夠高
I say it's already the best in the world
我說已經是世界最好的
that's useless
那沒有用
It is true that the user does not know his technical details at all
就是真的user是完全不知道他的技術細節
His pickiness is the truest
他的挑剔是最真實的
Let's now look at the United States in this
那我們現在看一下美國在這個
hollywood they do this
好萊塢他們對這個
Any new field his imagination is super shallow
任何的新的領域他的想像力都是超淺的
So let's look at this
所以我們看一下在這個
What the film industry expects from AI
電影界對AI的期望
2001 space exploration written, this was done in 1968, I don't know how many people read it
2001太空探寫,這是1968做的,我不知道有多少人看過
At that time it was Stanley Kubrick, he wrote a supercomputer number HAL
那個時候就是Stanley Kubrick,他寫了一個supercomputer號HAL
That is, the captain of the spaceship talks to the computer entirely by voice
就是那個這個太空船上船長完全用語音跟這個電腦對話
Then why is this account a very good computer, because every word of it is in front of IBM
那這個號為什麼是一個很好的電腦,因為他每一個字都在IBM前
That is to say, he deliberately regarded IBM as the best computer, and every letter of HAL is one in front of IBM.
就是說他故意把IBM當成一個最好的電腦,HAL每一個字母都在IBM前面一個
So he was in front of IBM, and behind that there was an AI artificial intelligence in 2001, and many people have seen it
所以他是底IBM前面,那後面2001有個AI artificial intelligence,也很多人看過
This is the first robot that knows what love is, so his love is quite scary, that is to say, in unconditional
這是第一個會知道什麼叫love的機器人,那他這個love也蠻可怕的,就是說在沒有條件的
so by the end his mother was freaking out
所以到後來他的母親都嚇壞了
2004 Public Enemy of Robots, which means that every house has 3 to 5 robots to do all the house cleaning
2004機械公敵,這是說每一家都有3到5個機器人當,做所有家裡清潔
Later, the robot was disobedient and had some problems.
後來這個機械人不聽話就出了一些問題
Piano player in the cloud 2013
雲端琴人 2013年
this person is totally lonely
這個人完全很寂寞
He completely uses this text message
他完全用這個text message
Chatting with another invisible person
跟另外一個看不見的人在聊天
a woman
一個女的
that's called semansa
那個叫semansa
After talking, he really felt that he loved him very much.
聊到後來他是真的覺得說很愛他
But he once asked him a question
但是他有一次問他一個問題
He said how many people are you dating at the same time
他說你同時跟多少人在談戀愛
He said 365
他說365個
Also this terrible thing
同時就是這件很可怕的事情
So the comprehensive plan for 2014
所以2014年全面計畫
That means this is a scientist played by Johnny Depp
就是說這個是強尼戴普演的一個科學家
Then at this time he can continue his life
然後這個時候他把生命都可以延續下去
this is a new idea
這是一個新的一個想法
Then let me talk about it now
那我現在特別講一下
AlphaGo and Natural Language Understanding
AlphaGo和自然語言的理解
These two discrepancies correspond to natural language for machines
這兩個差異症對機器而言自然語言的符合
responsible for far more than the period
負責都遠遠超過為期
Because there are many self-evident common sense
因為原有很多不言而喻的常識
derived or derived knowledge
運喊或衍生的知識
For example, before you get off work today
譬如說你今天下班前
In Line, your wife sent a message saying
在Line裡面你太太打了一個Message說
no cooking tonight
今天晚上不做飯
what does that mean
那是什麼意思
there are two
有兩個
one for learning and one for excellence
一則以習一則以優
it's good to say
就是好的話就是說
Two can go out and find a good
兩個可以出去找個好
delicious restaurant, right?
好吃的飯店對不對
The other one is to say what are you doing around here today?
另外一個就是說你今天到處做什麼事
forgot something so he doesn't cook
又忘了什麼事所以他不做飯
then this thing
那這個東西的話
It is a bit difficult for a machine to understand
要機器了解是有點困難
Language understanding is often associated with larger contacts
語言理解往往和較大的contact
So this contact is
所以這個contact就是
The environment in which he spoke today
今天的整個他講話的環境
Like what's the news today
比如今天又有什麼新聞
A lot of these things are contact
一大堆這些東西都是contact
how do you know where he is from
你怎麼知道他是從哪裡
Get some Message written by
得到一些Message寫的
The relatively simple rules for the term
相對為期的規則相當簡單
The rule is that you surround each other
為期規則就是你把對方圍起來
Then he dies with only one eye left
然後他只剩一個眼就死掉
die with only one eye left
只剩一個眼就死掉
Now all artificial intelligence
那現在所有人工智慧
can go to see
可以去看
our video today
我們今天的視頻
How about thank you all
不如謝謝大家
thank you all
謝謝大家
Everything that is done on this is a single
在這個上面做的事情都是一個單一的
objective optimization
objective optimization
like the goal of surrounding him is to win
像圍起他的目標就是要贏
So he put a lot of chessboards down
所以他把很多棋盤下來下去
The end result is win or lose
最後結果是贏是輸
make this the last goal
把這個當作最後目標
Now this deep learning is very well trained in this area
現在這個深度學習他在這方面的訓練非常好
He can even play with himself
他甚至也可以自己跟自己下
He can memorize the result when he wins or loses at the end
上到最後輸贏他就可以把這個結果背起來
Then do a lot of interesting analysis below
然後去做下面很多有趣的分析
The earliest computer worker Turin
最早這個電腦職婦Turin
It's a pity to live to be 42 years old
很可惜活著42歲
He thought of a test
他就想到一個測試
Is it a machine or a human?
就是一個機器是不是人
Do you have the ability to approach people?
是不是有接近人的能力
A simple test he did
他做的一個簡單測試
Just put a tester in the first room
就是在第一個房間裡面放了一個測試者
one person
一個人
Put two computers in the second room
第二個房間放兩個電腦
one is real
一個是真的人
is also a terminal
也是terminal
you can message him
你可以打message給他
A machine is a piece of software
機器是一個軟體
So if the person on the left
所以如果這個左邊這個人
he can't tell
他分不出來
he can give him 30 minutes
他可以給他30分鐘時間
If he can't tell which one is the machine
他如果分不出來哪一個是機器
which one is human
哪一個是人
that machine is successful
那個機器就是成功的
so he said this
所以他說這個
what is understanding
什麼叫理解
is the last
就是最後
You can't tell if he's a human or a machine
你分不出來他是人還是機器
So AI research
所以AI的研究
Heart failure ups and downs are very many times
心衰起伏是非常多次
This is a
這是一個
Norville Economist
Norville經濟學家
winner of economics
經濟講的獲獎人
Herb assignment famous
Herb assignment 很有名的
at Connected Manor
在Connected Manor
他說Machine will be capable within 20 years
他說Machine will be capable within 20 years
of doing any work a man can do
of doing any work a man can do
This was spoken in 1965
這1965年講的
1985 is about to happen
1985年就要實現了
everyone knows no
大家都知道沒有
AI rehearsals are in
AI的排練是在
Scholars at MIT
MIT的學者
Marvin Minsky
Marvin Minsky
two years after him in 1967
在1967年比他晚兩年
He said within a generation
他說 within a generation
the problem of creating artificial intelligence
the problem of creating artificial intelligence
was substantially be solved
was substantially be solved
So because of these people's
所以因為他們這些人的
So a lot of research funding is thrown away
所以很多的研究經費丟下去
But the effect is very limited
但是成效非常有限
So let's look at some examples of failure
那我們現在看一些失敗的例子
This is of course more expensive.
這個當然是比較花錢花得多
so i put it here
所以我才放到這兒
Japan's fifth-generation computer in 1982
日本第五代電腦1982年
At that time, Japan's national power was very strong.
那個時候日本的國力非常的強盛
they have a lot of money
他們的錢非常多
so what
所以呢
He wanted to create a computer that was fast and could understand people
他想創造一個又快又能理解人的電腦
The result is nothing
結果是不了了之
Let it go
不了了之
This Japanese compares
這個日本人比較
He is inside
他對內啊
for being quick to admit mistakes
因為很快就承認錯誤
But he doesn't want to admit his mistakes
但是對外他不願意承認錯誤
so how do we know
所以我們後來怎麼知道
because he made a famous
因為他做了一個很有名的
so-called battery point
所謂的電子池點
He thinks this electronic pool point is all-encompassing
他認為這個電子池點無所不包
can solve many human problems
可以解決人類很多的問題
when he finally finished
最後他結束的時候
This electronic battery point
這個電子池點
He would have sold millions
他本來賣幾百萬
Later, you can buy it for 10,000 Taiwan dollars
後來一萬台幣就可以買到
It's basically called a jump price
基本上是叫跳樓價
no one wants
沒有人要
Another CYC Project is also a
另外一個CYC Project也是一個
very famous 1984
非常有名的1984年
there is a very
有一個非常
He wants to collect a lot of try
他就希望去收集很多嘗試
Then the computer can think like a human in the future
然後把電腦以後可以像人一樣思考
He tried to use logic to choose
他這個嘗試都用邏輯去選
because at that time logic was what they used most
因為那時候邏輯是他們最常使用
But this project later because there is no specific application
但是這個project後來因為沒有具體應用
while daytime demonstrations
而日間示威
he still exists
他現在還是存在
But you can also go to license
但是你也可以去licence
But very few people use it
可是要用的人非常少
Because they never thought about how to use my knowledge
因為他們當初沒有想過說我這個知識怎麼用
so it's a pity
所以這是非常可惜的一個
And this one is full...
還有這個是滿...
Japan's entrance examination robots set their goals in 2014
日本聯考機器人他們的目標2014年訂的
To be admitted to the University of Tokyo
要考上東京大學
Just like our entrance exam
就像我們聯考一樣
We have about five or six subjects
我們大概有五六科嘛
Each subject will give you textbook reference books
每一科都給你課本參考書
Or some related news?
或者是相關的一些新聞啊什麼
You can go to the exam like a human
你就可以去跟人一樣去考試
Then this thing is not only made in Japan
那這個東西不是只有日本在做
Mainland China spent 20 billion yuan
中國大陸花了200億人民幣
about two years ago
在大概兩年前
voted two or three years ago
兩三年前投下去
20 billion, let's not talk about RMB
200億我們不要講人民幣
Our NT$20 billion
我們台幣200億
20 billion also happened from there
200億也從那邊發生過
he's just in this one
他光是在這一個
Robots 20 billion yuan was spent on exam robots
機器人 考試機器人上花了200億人民幣
for about a dozen schools
給大概十幾個學校去做
They hope that within three to five years
他們希望在三年五年之內就
This time the Japanese are more honest
這次日本人比較誠實
he gave up last year
他在去年就放棄了
because they found
因為他們發現
Now the score is about the middle and lower grades
現在得分大概是中下的等級
I just can't get into that public university
就是考不到那個公立大學
Probably private universities can be admitted
大概私立大學可以考上
but the computer you need to know
但電腦你要知道
he is very rambunctious
他非常賴皮
because he never forgets
因為他顧目不忘
all historical geography
所有歷史地理東西
remember everything clearly
全部都記得清清楚楚
so you test him
所以你跟他考試
But there is one thing he must lose
但有一點他一定輸他的
But his current method is difficult to break through
但是他的目前的方法很難突破
so he thinks
所以他覺得說
this is probably hopeless
這個大概沒有希望
the successful case
那成功的案例的話
It's all this commercial company
都是這個commercial company
IBM Sunland beats the king of western gas
IBM 森蘭打敗西洋氣氣王
At that time they were
那那個時候他們在
It is assumed that this game of Go may be 50 years later
預設這個圍棋可能要50年以後
will defeat
才會打敗
Because the maintenance complexity may be tens of millions of times
因為維持的複雜度可能是向其報幾千萬倍
That IBM Watson Beats the Jeopardy Champion
那IBM Watson打敗Jeopardy冠軍
Jeopardy is a simple question answering system
Jeopardy是一個簡單的問答系統
so he might ask if you are the winner of the physics prize in 1998
所以他可能問你是1998年物理獎的得主
Who is it? Questions like this
是誰啊類似這樣的問題
That's about speed
那個是要比速度的
so the computer
所以電腦
We all thought he was voice input at first
他當初我們都以為他是語音輸入
then just like people
然後跟人一樣
actually not
其實不是
Later he was rambunctious
後來他賴皮
He means the examiner
他就是說這個考官
It's the show host
就是節目主持人
when starting to read the topic
在開始念題目的時候
He just presses a key to put the text
他就按一個鍵把那個text
Already written text questions
已經寫好的text 問題
send to computer
傳給電腦
So the computer has five or six seconds
所以電腦有五六秒的時間
He can calculate while reciting the title
在念題目的時候他就可以計算
In this case he will press the button
這樣的話他去按那個鈕
will be faster than people
會比人要快
So this is a bit unreasonable
所以這個是有點不太合理
The way IBM wins
那IBM這個贏的方式
actually
其實也是
really a big project
真的是一個大工程
He spent 25 engineer
他花了25個engineer
are very advanced
都是很高級
IBM engineer
IBM的engineer
five years
五年的時間
plus there is
再加上有
Many schools cooperate with him
非常多的學校跟他一起合作
Then what
然後呢
every question asked
每一個問題問出來
He'll have 100 different systems
他會有100個不同的系統
to come up with an answer
去提出答案
some systems
有的系統他
It is the kind of confidence that is relatively high
就是那種confidence比較高
Some systems are lower
有的系統比較低
he will just vote
他就會光投個票
He'll find out the answer
他就會把那個答案就找出來
he didn't use
那他並不是用
the way we call understanding
我們所謂的理解的方式
naa fago
那阿發購
This is really quite powerful
這個是真的是相當厲害
Google AFAGO
Google 阿發購
It's not Google's own
也不是Google自己產生
Also bought the one from the UK
也是去買英國的那個
a company
一個公司
Then Google and do it again
然後再Google再做
beat korean flag
打敗韓國旗
Go back to Banner King
回去旗王
deep learning
裡面用深入學習
this is part
這是一部分
and many other tricks
還有很多其他的技巧
But the way he and humans set the flag
但他和人類下旗方式
very different
大不相同
all of us
我們所有一位
Teacher Xu Zhansheng
徐戰生老師
He is making a banner
他在做相旗
Then he every week
那他每個禮拜
will invite a Xiangqi Master
都會請一個相旗大師
come talk to him for an hour
來跟他聊一個小時
I use my old man to purchase
用老夫採購
this
這個
He said every flag of the master
他說大師每一首旗子
considering
考慮到
Two or three possible moves, why so few
兩三個可能落子,為什麼那麼少
That is to say, when ordinary people play chess
就是說一般人在下棋的時候
90% impossible to win the paper
有90%不可能贏的那個紙
you don't even think about it
你都不會去考慮
just don't watch at all
就是根本就看都不會看
But the master is 99%
但是大師是99%
Even 99.9% he won't consider
甚至99.9%他不會考慮
so you can see in
所以你可以看到在
Some parks have a really good camera operator
有些公園裡面有一個很厲害的相機師
He can play with 10 people at the same time
他可以同時跟10個人下
He walked to the second place after he got off.
他這個人下完走到第二個地方
Just get off the chair and walk back like this
就下椅子這樣走回來
The first one hasn't been downloaded yet
第一個還沒下
It means only thinking about the actual species every time
就是每下一子只思考實際種
Because you want to think about where the other party might go next
因為你下一子要想對方可能下哪裡
So there are quite a few steps here and there.
所以這一來一去有蠻多的這個步
So in this case you consider two or three possibilities
所以這樣的話你考慮兩三個可能
You can't remember all this in your head
你這個腦袋就已經記不完
So the great thing is
所以其實厲害的是
These masters with such a small head
這些大師他那麼小的一個腦袋
Calculations are so slow and memory is so poor
計算那麼慢,記憶力又那麼差
How could he be in such a fast time
他怎麼可以在這麼快的時間
Just finish thinking about this actual possibility
把這實際可能想完就結束
Many untimely directions have been automatically deleted in the previous life
前一世已經將許多不合時方向自動刪除
Our feeling is that the result of his talk with the master is that someone actually memorized a lot of patterns
我們的感覺是他跟大師談的結果是有人其實記了很多pattern
like you say it like so many of your old photos
就像你這樣講,就像你的很多以前的照片
You don't remember very clearly, but you know where you have been and what movies you have been looking for
你也不是記得很清楚,但是你知道你去過什麼地方玩,找過什麼片
There is a similar experience in the next issue
在下期裡面也有類似的一個經驗
After downloading, he will have many such patterns left behind.
就下完以後他會有很多這種pattern留下來
These patterns can help him do a quick search
這些pattern能夠幫助他去做很快的搜尋
I told Mr. Xu Zhuansheng that now Afagou has won against Weiqi
我就跟徐專生老師說,現在阿發購已經贏了維奇
It's Master Vicky, what research can you do now?
就是維奇大師,你現在還有什麼研究可以做
He said that in fact, in their direction
他說其實現在他們方向
This is the current Deep Learning, it is impossible for AFAGO to do it
這個是現在Deep Learning,阿發購不太可能做
That is to say, how computers can help people improve, you will scare others
就是說電腦如何幫助人進步,你會嚇贏別人
like my pool coach is doing too
就像我的桌球教練也在做
You said the world champion pool must be very good
你說世界冠軍桌球一定打得很好
If we saw him, we would lose confidence
如果看了他我們就沒信心了
Exercising is boring, it's not like that
運動就沒意思,其實不是這樣
I hope that you can make more progress at your current level
都希望說在你目前的層次上能夠更進步
so you want a coach
所以你想找教練
Then this computer plays chess
那這個電腦這個下棋
he can't teach you
他沒有辦法教你
He can't explain why he won
他也不能解釋為什麼他會贏
So this is actually very little help to us.
所以這個對我們人幫助其實很少
What we need is actually a game that is more like a human playing chess.
我們需要其實是一個比較像人下棋那樣
I'll tell you what's wrong with this step.
就跟你講說這一步下去會有什麼壞處
see it right away
馬上就看出來
Such a study is actually relevant to the current
這樣的一個研究其實對現在的這個
All machine learning is Machine Impossible
所有的機器學習都是Machine Impossible
at least now i can see that
至少現在我看得到是這樣
OK, let me show you a simple
好那我這裡給各位看一個簡單的
empathetic robot
善解人意的機器人
What does it mean to have everything but ventilation
什麼叫萬事具備只欠通風
Here's this sparring system for billiards
這裡有一個桌球的這個對打系統
Just opposite here is a computer robot
就對面這邊是一個那個電腦機器人
Then you see how good he is
然後你看他多厲害
The oil of this machine is its ability, right?
這個機器的油,就是它能力很強對不對
nothing can kill
怎麼都打不死
I just wanted to say that if he could teach me
我就想說,如果他會教我的話
Then the coach is out of work, right?
那麼教練就沒工作了對不對
What does it mean that this computer owes Dongfeng now?
這個電腦現在欠東風什麼意思
He doesn't know, he doesn't understand my shortcomings
他不知道,就不了解我的缺點
then what
然後怎麼
He has no so-called strategy concept now
他現在沒有所謂的策略概念
that he wants to win
就是他想要贏
Of course it's too easy for him to beat me now
當然他現在贏我太容易了
Just because I can't even kill him
就說因為我都打不死他嘛
But what he wants to teach me is to
但是他要教我這件事就是要
The meaning of being kind
要善體的意義
where is my shortcoming
我的缺點在哪裡
He told me how your knowledge changed
他跟我講說你知識怎麼改變
you can fight whatever you want
你就可以打怎麼樣
can't do it
沒辦法做的
So language understanding is generally regarded as the highest level of intelligence
所以語言理解一般被視為最高等級的智慧
When the robot arrives, if the language ability can be strengthened
機械人到了如果能夠加強語言能力
Become better at communicating and directing
變得更好溝通、指揮
There are more places that can help manpower
就可以幫助人力的地方更多
like internet of things
像物聯網
The Internet of Things is actually connecting all the things in the home to the Internet.
物聯網其實就是把所有家裡的東西都能夠上網
can be strung together
都能夠串起來
There is also a mark on the milk in the refrigerator
像冰箱的那個牛奶上面也有一個記號
It can know when to buy new milk
它可以知道說什麼時候需要再去買新的牛奶
What kind of fruit is also on each of them
什麼水果也是每個上面都有
Sports and leisure
運動休閒
The exercise we just talked about
剛才我們講的運動
This table tennis might be the fastest
這個桌球可能是速度最快了
you want to play tennis
你要打網球
You don't play with machines at all
你根本不要跟機械玩
Word processing for slow formulas
慢公式的文書處理
This is the future administrative secretary should be careful
這是以後行政秘書也要小心
just a lot of work
就很多工作
Not everything it does can be replaced by a computer
並不是所有的它做事都可以被電腦取代
It means that 80% can replace
而是說80%可以取代
Now there is only one secretary, it only needs to handle the remaining 20%
現在只要一個秘書,它只要處理剩下百分之二十就夠了
So this is a terrible environment
所以這種是很可怕的一個環境
Natural language understanding, let me briefly tell you about it now
自然語言理解我現在大概簡單跟各位講一下
It is of course my personal opinion that it needs to be bumpy inside
裡面需要的坎坷的,這當然是我個人的見解
If you do learn natural language, we have a colleague here
如果照作有學自然語言,我們有位同事在這裡
I probably won't be too convinced after hearing it.
大概就聽了就不太服氣
natural language concepts
自然語言概念
In fact, the concept of natural language is quite vague
自然語言其實它的概念相當模糊
and it's hard to define
而且很難定義清楚
Like I said Fascinating Article, right?
像我講Fascinating Article對不對
This is Fascinating to me
這是對我講Fascinating
what you see may be different
你看的話可能不一樣
A good way to do it, what does that mean?
A good way to do it,這什麼意思啊?
A good tennis player
A good tennis player
This one is more confusing that is
這個是更 confusing 就是說
Everyone's ability to play tennis is different
每一個人的打網球的能力都不一樣
So I say good, maybe others say it is very common
所以我講 good 也許是人家講是很普通的
So these words, but we usually speak like this
所以這些話,但是我們平常講話就是這樣講
Do you understand?
大家聽得懂?
A good student
A good student
Then you know what it means, right?
那你也知道什麼意思嘛,對不對
However, what does it mean to be unwavering
但是,重規重矩什麼叫撲偏不移
The honest method, the method is actually very difficult
誠實手法,手法其實很難啦
Because have you ever read "Mingfa", "Xingfa" or something?
因為你有沒有讀過《明法》、《行法》什麼
A dozen pairs of what corporate law
一打對那個什麼公司法
you haven't read it, how did you suffer
你都沒讀過,你怎麼受
So, wait a minute, let's talk about
所以,等一下我們就講一下說
what these things how we run in the world
什麼這些東西我們在世界上是怎麼去運行的
good student
好學生
Let's mention that these concepts have their context
我們再提到這些概念都有它的上下文
background, the background of this conversation and this context
背景,這個談話背景和這段上下文
allows you to bring this convergence
可以讓你把這個收斂
So if you talk to someone who can't stand it at the train station
所以,如果在火車站你跟受不了的人講
Kaohsiung, Taipei, then he will immediately
台北高雄,那他馬上就
I almost ask you what time it will be over
差不多問你幾點鐘就結束
You usually don't understand what you say
你平常講這種話,你就聽不懂
Therefore, understanding different levels is actually related to many
所以理解不同層次,其實跟很多
The question answering system thing is very similar
問答系統的事情非常相似
some questions may be easy to answer
有的問題可能很容易回答
Answers to some questions may be equivalent to a doctoral or master's thesis
有的問題的答案可能相當於博士碩士論文
So understanding is the same, some are easy, some are very easy
所以理解也是一樣,有的很容易,有的非常容易
What we are interested in today is to talk about the understanding ability required by service robots
我們今天有興趣的是談服務性的機器人所需要的理解能力
basically he needs to be able to take basic instructions
基本上他要能夠接受基本指令
Then you can have a conversation, it's not easy if you can have a conversation
然後可以對談,可以對談就不容易
like when we often ask questions
像我們常常問問題的時候
Because I went to the bank to ask questions
因為我到銀行去問問題
don't understand their terminology
不懂他們的專業名詞
so i talked for a long time
所以我講了半天
Well, if he is a pilot, he can understand
那個,如果是個行員他可以聽得懂
He just turned it into saying that you want to deposit a fixed deposit, right?
他才把它轉成說你是要存定存對不對
We didn't know the word fixed deposit, so we talked for a long time
我們不知道定存這個字就講了半天
the same goes for robots
機器人也是一樣
today you ask a question
今天你問一個問題
Can he narrow down the scope of his problem quickly?
他可不可以把他那個問題範圍很快縮小
It's better to give suggestions
比較厲害的是提建議
say like my wife
像我內人就講說
his students often
他的學生常常
I ask him how to do everything
什麼事情都是問他怎麼做
Then he told him that he would run to that city
然後他跟他講,他就去跑那個城市
to be able to make suggestions
要能夠提建議的話
This robot can replace that student
這個機器人就可以把那個學生給取代掉
What many of our master students do now
我們現在很多碩士學生做的事情
To be honest, it can really be replaced in the future
說實話以後真的是可以取代
Do you want to study for a doctorate in the future, or don't study for a master's degree
以後要不要就讀博士 要不然就不要讀碩士
computing words words
computing words words
we think
我們認為說
Computing is to calculate this thing, which seems to be done by a person who is good at mathematics.
computing就計算這個東西好像是一個數學好的人才在做
But if you look carefully at the following questions, you will find that everyone can do it and very quickly
可是你仔細看下面的問題 你發現所有人都會做 而且很快
why is this
這個是為什麼
May I ask what is the floating rate of the second-year fixed deposit in US dollars?
我們請問美金二年級定存的浮動力率是多少
This is very clear, right?
這個很清楚嘛 對不對
Immediately take out this watch from the computer
馬上電腦就把這個表拿出來
Two-year float rate here 1.15
二年期浮動力率在這裡 1.15
If he says one less
如果說他少講一個
May I ask what is the interest rate of the second-year fixed deposit in US dollars?
請問美金二年級定存的力率是多少
The customer service will immediately ask him whether the power rate is fixed or floating
客服馬上跟他會反問是固定還是浮動力率
How hard is it for a computer to do this today
電腦今天要做到這件事有多困難
Or what is the floating rate of the US dollar fixed deposit?
或者他講美金定存的浮動力率是多少
This seldom-speaking second grader will immediately ask back how many months
這少講的二年級 他馬上就會反問是幾個月起
So today if you say
所以今天如果說
I want to replace this customer service, as long as I can answer these questions like him
我要取代這個客服,我只要能夠跟他一樣把這些問題
Make up for what is missing
能夠缺的地方補回去
Then why did he know there would be a shortage of these things?
那他為什麼知道會缺這些東西
So in fact when you're talking
所以事實上你在講話的時候
Are you talking about a constraint
你是在講一個限制條件
Then there is a deficiency in this condition, and he will know it immediately
那這條件裡面有一個缺的,他馬上就知道
This man is very powerful
這個人是非常厲害的
Then you may ask why you can’t talk about the following
那你會問說為什麼不能講下面
What are the benefits of a two-year floating time deposit in US dollars?
請問美金浮動二年期定存的利益是多少
Sounds weird that the float runs here
聽起來很奇怪,浮動跑到這裡
because every word he has his best friend
因為每一個字他有他的好朋友
with less good friends, less familiar friends
和不太好的朋友,比較不熟的朋友
when you go to sit at a table outside
那你去外面坐一桌子的時候
You'll find that your best friend is sitting next to you
你會發現說那個好朋友就坐旁邊
This float is the best friend of interest rates
這浮動是利率的好朋友
he can't sit next to the sophomore
他就不能坐在二年期旁邊
then we are on the computer
那我們在電腦上面
In fact, all these things can be calculated
其實已經把這些東西都可以算得出來
which things are close to which things
是哪些東西跟哪些東西要接近
Sometimes order is very important, this is the order just mentioned
秩序有時候很重要,這個就是剛剛講的秩序
jokes from my time
以前我這年代的笑話
Most of you probably haven't heard of it
大部分人都可能沒聽過
there is a foreigner
有一個外國人
Americans learn English
美國人學英文
No, he learned Chinese and came to Taiwan
不是 他有學中文到台灣來
when he got off the plane
那他下飛機的時候
he will be a little bit
他會一點點
he just wants to show off
他就想要秀一下
the girl who came to pick up the plane
那來接機的一個女孩
looks very beautiful
長得非常漂亮
he tensed up
他一下緊張
he said against
他就講反
he was going to talk about you
他本來要講你好嗎
just the other way around
就反過來講
hello mom
媽好你
The girl froze for a moment
那女孩在愣了一下
do not understand at all
完全聽不懂
Then he didn't see it right
那他一看不對
he just thinks about it
他就想一想
He wants to usually say hello to your mother
他想通常說你媽好
the girl
這女孩
just smiled a little
就是稍微笑了一下
still pretty embarrassing
還是蠻尷尬
This man is still wrong
這個男人想說還是不對
So in the end he figured it must be right
所以最後他想出來一定對
hello mom
媽你好
So this is such a simple sequence
所以這個這麼簡單一個次序
when you usually talk
你平常講話的時候
Didn't think about it, didn't think about it, right?
沒有去想 沒有想對不對
just say it
你就講出來
that's why
那這是為什麼
very interesting
很有趣的
so you
所以你
must be seen as a language constraint
一定可以看成一個語言的限制條件
In fact, the language has many restrictions
其實語言有很多限制條件
then why do we know how to say
那我們為什麼知道怎麼講
In fact, we have a lot of panels in our minds
其實我們有很多Panel放腦子裡
You don't even have to think about it to generate these automatically
你都不需要思考就會自動產生這些
will automatically understand what others say
也會自動了解別人講的
so today we
所以我們今天
At least the model I made is to learn these Panels
至少我做的模型就是把這些Panel給學下來
What about the two-year fixed deposit interest rate in US dollars we asked just now?
那剛才我們問的美金二年期定存利率啊
what those things
什麼那些東西
It's a condition
這是一個條件嘛
If you don’t make sense, the conditions are met
不make sense就是條件滿足
If you don’t make sense, you still have some conditions
不make sense就是你還差了一些條件
ok
ok
If your language skills are not good enough
那如果說你那個語言能力不行
Like the English we just arrived in the United States
像我們剛到美國那個英文
understand every word
每個字都聽得懂
But I don't understand that sentence
但那句話意識不懂
It means what is the condition
就是表示那個條件是什麼
what is the meaning of its whole condition
它整個條件構成的意義是什麼
have no idea
不知道
So elementary school math wheel word problem
所以小學數學輪字題
It's a very simple quiz
就是一個很簡單的測驗
We're doing language analysis inside
我們在做語言分析裡面
this is all inside
這個是所有裡面
The so-called least attempted program in elementary school
所謂的嘗試最少的在小學的程式
Everyone knows that computers are now doing these problems
各位知道現在電腦來做這些問題
to what extent
可以做到什麼程度
Recently at MIT they used machine learning to do this
最近MIT他們用機器學習做這個
Average 50 points
平均50分
Even the one who looks like a child will probably get 50 points in the test
就是連那個像小孩子大概考50分會
get spanked at home
回家會被打屁股
It's just that there is no child who is worse than him in the exam
就是沒有一個小孩考得比他差
This sounds simple to us
這個我們聽起來很簡單嘛
Xiaomi has two apples
小米有兩個蘋果
30 kilometers cut two
30千米 削了兩隻
His difficulty is
他這難的地方是
He did not sharpen two pencils
他沒有削了兩隻鉛筆
fill it in yourself
要自己把它填進去
ate an apple
吃了一個蘋果
How many apples does Xiaomi have?
請問小米還有幾個蘋果
Computers are now equally difficult
現在電腦也是同樣困難
After reading this, he doesn't know what you are doing
他這個看完他不知道你在幹什麼
Xiaohua's father is thirty years older than him
小華的爸爸比他大三十歲
in two years
再過兩年
His dad is twice his age
他爸爸的年齡就是他的兩倍
How old is Xiao Hua now?
請問小華現在幾歲
It's all a constitutional condition
這都是一個憲政條件
So understand quickly
所以懂得很快就
So the reason why they won't do it
所以他們這個上面不會做的原因
But because I don't understand this reason
但是因為聽不懂這個原因
Then we asked about restaurant tea science, like Siri actually has restaurant tea science,
然後我們再問餐廳茶學,像Siri上面居然就有餐廳茶學,
We are looking for a meal, what can we get next to the Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hall,
我們要找一個餐菜在國父紀念館旁邊拿什麼東西,
You don't need to ask him, and now you can't,
你可以不問他,現在也不行了,
That is to say, he can only do voice translation for you now,
就是說他現在只能幫你做語音翻譯,
The question is too complicated to answer, that is, he can't make sense,
太複雜問題不能回答,就是他不能make sense,
He doesn't know whether the conditions for your speech are met or what you want to do,
他不知道你講話的條件是是不是滿足或者是你要幹什麼,
So just input these conditions into the computer,
所以只要把這些條件輸入到電腦裡面,
Computers can answer more things,
電腦就可以回答更多事情,
Serial drama this is Cliff Hanger,
連續劇這個是Cliff Hanger,
That is to say, the suspense we just mentioned is the condition of a sentence,
就是說懸疑我們剛剛講是一句話的條件,
You can talk about a story, and a story also has its beginnings and transitions,
你可以說一個story,一個story也有起承轉合,
In the end, what does the so-called successful conclusion of this story mean?
最後這個story的所謂圓滿結束什麼意思,
Even if this person is not married, did that person have a successful relationship in the end?
就是這個人也沒結婚,那個人最後有沒有談戀愛成功啊,
these things
就是這些事嘛,
Cliff Hanger is actually a fulfillment condition,
Cliff Hanger其實就是也是一個滿足條件,
Originally, he acted in ten episodes of the American series,
本來在美國連續劇他演十集,
Taiwan can play 40 episodes,
台灣可以演四十集,
He hangs there all the time, and he can add a lot of encryption
他就一直懸在那裡,就可以增添加密大堆
So, computing with words is a very interesting
所以,computing with words是一個滿有趣的
That is, you didn’t just say that there is only one sentence, your story also has an ending
就是你不是說只有一句話,你一個story也有一個ending
How do you find out this ending
你怎麼去把這個ending給找出來
So if you think about it carefully
那所以你仔細想的話
Every sentence we see on the Internet is make sense
我們在網路上看每一句話都是make sense
Most people need to make sense when speaking
一般人講話都需要make sense
So he has some restrictions
所以他都是有一些限制條件
But the literary exception
但是是文學例外
Why is literature an exception
文學為什麼例外
what do you say i'm in a
你說我在一個什麼
cool night
青涼的夜晚
Walk alone on the beach hill
獨自在沙灘山漫步
Thinking of yesterday's banquet
想到昨天的宴會
There's a lot of this kind of talk that doesn't serve any purpose
這些都沒有任何目的的這種話很多
let's not talk now
我們現在不談了
Today we are talking about service machinery people
我們今天講service服務機械的人
Including carpet cleaning
包括地毯清乾淨
clean the sofa
沙發抹乾淨
This is a very clear instruction
這個是很清楚的指令
or turn on the air conditioner
或者把冷氣開強
So these conditions are actually the so-called knowledge
所以這些條件其實它就是所謂的知識
If you have this knowledge you will have a way to understand and then you can answer
你有這些知識的話你就有辦法了解 然後可以回答
Then why is it like the two edges of a calendar sword
那它為什麼像一把歷劍的兩刃
because you have this knowledge structure
因為你有這個知識結構
So when you're dealing with a very complex problem
所以你在處理很複雜的問題的時候
a very complicated sentence you can understand very quickly
一個很複雜的句子你可以很快了解
But it also limits human thinking
但是它同樣極限人的思考
This is when we do research
這就是我們做研究的時候
why do you sometimes jump out
為什麼有時候要跳出來
Go to a third party to see why you are doing the right thing
到一個第三者來看說你這樣做為什麼是不是對的
For example, the doctor's concept of health is what my wife said.
比如醫生的健康概念這是我太太講的
A doctor may see patients for a lifetime
醫生他一輩子看病人大概有
Say he has a few thousand
說他有幾千個好了
that number is still very small
那個數目還是非常少
He has some conclusions, you need to be healthy
他就有一些conclusion 你要健康
It's the fact that we do a lot of these health studies
就是其實我們做很多這些健康的研究
Tens of thousands of people have been following them for an unknown number of years before reaching a conclusion
都是幾萬人跟蹤了不知道多少年才得到結論
But most of us rely on his impression
但是我們一般人都是憑他的印象
so you become more stubborn
所以你會變得比較偏頑
Georgian Airlines
格航格航
this is for us
這個是對我們這個
The academicians of Academia Sinica specially remind
中研院的院士特別提醒一下
Our academicians often go to various institutes to ask questions
我們院士經常到各所去質詢
The question said everyone went up to report, right?
那質詢說就是每個人上去報告對不對
Some fields are not related to him.
有的領域不是跟他其實沒什麼關係
But he has a lot of insights
可是他見解非常多
We can't say that what you said is wrong, what?
我們也不能說你這個講的不對啊什麼
can't say that
不能這樣講
So it's very polite
所以就是很客氣的
so
所以
this is why
這個就是為什麼是
a sharp blade
一把利刃
everyone has to be quite humble
每一個人都要相當謙虛
just go to a field
只要到一個領域
you are not very familiar
你不是非常熟的
right
對不對
Actually I'm talking about AS
其實我在講AS
I'm also worried
我也是很擔心的
That is to say, I may say something that is
就是說我可能講一些話是
It's totally different from what people say
跟人家講的完全不一樣
So don't believe me all
所以各位不要全部信我的
this
這個
This is to draw a Picture
這個就是畫一個Picture
above this is a
這上面是一個
a young woman
一個少婦嘛
eyes here nose here
眼睛在這裡鼻子在這裡
then wear one
然後戴一個
hat right?
帽子對不對
Did you guys see another image
各位有沒有看到另外一個圖像
This is often psychologically
這是心理學上常常
some examples
有的例子
this is an old woman
這個是一個老太婆
this is her jaw
這是她下巴
the same one
就是同樣的一個
If you take the lead and think so, you won't see the other picture
如果你先任為主,認為是這樣,你就看不到另外一個picture
We often do this, this is the understanding of an article paragraph
我們常常是這樣,這個是一個文章段落的理解
This is borrowed from the same article from the teacher Chen Yixin of National Taiwan University.
這是從那個台大陳一新老師那邊同一篇跟他借的
There are some conditions for the understanding of the sentence just mentioned
那剛才講一個句子的理解是有一些條件
This article paragraph is more complex
這個文章段落更複雜
So you guys have to admire yourselves very much
所以各位要非常敬佩你自己
When this sentence is finished, you fully understand
就是這句話講完的時候,你都完全了解
it's really not easy
實在是非常不容易
Why? It's unlikely that a computer will do it
為什麼?電腦要做的話不太可能
Although the new regulations and documents formulated by ordinary new districts are somewhat crude
儘管普通新區制定的法規新文件有些比較粗寒
Some are only provisional
有些還是只是暫行規定
have a halfway night in practice
有在實踐中途晚上
But this kind of legal system is only related to the practice of economic and social activities
但這種法制,僅跟經濟和社會活動的做法
Well received by domestic investors
受到了國內投資者的好評
They think that investing in ordinary new districts is not easy for Changhua.
他們認為到普通新區投資辦事有彰化
Rules and interests can be guaranteed
講規矩利益能得到保障
OK, if we want to analyze this
好,這個要分析的話
This is a formal analysis
這個是正式分析
I split the previous words into paragraphs.
我把前面的話就是一段一段分開
Each punctuation does not count as a paragraph, does it?
每個標點不太算一段對不對
This is despite the common area
這個是儘管普通區什麼什麼
Some of the latter are supplementary, so they are called parallel
後面有些這是補充,所以叫並列
To be gradually improved, this is a juxtaposition, but a juxtaposition of upper and lower positions, not a parallel
有待逐漸完善,這是一個並列,但是一個上下位的並列,不是一個平行的
The same is true here, this rule of law is an explanatory way, and then there are several juxtaposed with the following
那這邊也是一樣,這種法治是一個解說式的方式,然後跟下面又是幾個並列
Then explain it to him, the last is the turning point, the turning point means that in the end he thinks, at the beginning although he said that even though
然後跟他解說,最後是轉折,轉折就是說最後他認為,一開始雖然他是說儘管
Although there are a lot of shortcomings, but in the end I think there is still a way
儘管有什麼一大堆缺點,但是最後覺得是還是有張法
So when we look at it, we can understand it after reading it for a few seconds
所以我們在看的時候,一眼看回去大概幾秒鐘就看完就了解
So why can't the computer do it now, ideally he can do it
那為什麼電腦現在做不到,這是理想的情況他可以做到
Such an exaggerated understanding is very difficult for a computer
這麼一個偏張理解,對電腦是非常難
So everyone knows that when it comes to natural language understanding, our human ability is now far beyond that of computers
所以各位知道說自然語言理解,我們的人能力現在遠遠超過電腦
but there are many reasons
但原因很多
In the end, let's talk about what is called technique and what is called a good student at the beginning.
那最後我們把剛才一開始我們不是講什麼叫手法,什麼叫好學生啊
how to define
怎麼去定義
This is my definition, just listen to it
這是我的定義,聽聽就好
That is, for each language concept, we assume that there is a corresponding question bank
就是對於每個語言概念我們假設有一個對應的題庫
That is to say, you think of it as saying that I am going to test a child today
就是說你把它想成說我今天要考一個小孩子
Or a high school student, what questions are used to test him
或者一個高中生,用什麼題目考他
Then this computer passed the same test
那這個電腦經過同樣的考試
If the robot answers through this question bank
如果這個機械人回答通過這個題庫
The question bank must be sampled, some each time
題庫一定抽樣的,每次抽一些
Reaching 70% counts for a few
達到70%就算幾個
So let's say he understands the concept, not that he's 100%
那我們就說他了解這概念,不是說他100%
In fact, we are here, and it is the same when I take the value license test in the United States.
那其實我們在,我在美國考那個價值執照也是一樣
American Exam Value is next to an examiner's seat
美國考價值就是一個考官座旁邊
Then you pass and pass, right?
然後你過了就過了,對不對
He was glad that he was in a good mood that day, and many people had
他高興那天心情好了,很多人過
Otherwise, many people
要不然的話就很多人不過
when i go to the exam
我去考試的時候
I visited Stanford in 1996
我是在1996年到Stanford訪問
At that time, I had been driving in Taiwan for a long time
那時候我已經在台灣開了非常久車
Everyone knows the level of technology in Taiwan
大家都知道台灣那個技術水準
There must be no problem driving in the US, right?
到美國開一定不會有任何問題,對不對
But I passed the exam three times
但是我考了三次才過
Because he asked me about you as soon as he got in the car
因為他一上車就問我說你
Do you know how to drive it? I said it has been open for 20 years
你會不會開?我說開了20年
This sentence alone has already deducted a lot of points from him.
光這句話就已經被他扣很多分了
So in fact, he also has his own problems.
所以其實就是說他也有他的題目
he picks a few questions
他隨便挑幾題
For example, you make me a Pair of parking
譬如說你給我做一個Pair of parking
leather parking or something
皮型停車啊什麼的
Back into the garage, these things
倒車入庫啊這些東西
it's over if you know
你會的話就過了
It's basically not that difficult to understand here
那這裡了解基本上並沒有這麼困難
We are in a general company
我們在一般的公司啊
or we in society
或是我們在社會上
Many things have exam certification
很多東西有考試認證
So as long as we can handle a concept
所以只要我們能好好處理一個概念的
relevant knowledge to be able to understand the concept
相關知識就能夠理解這個概念
In fact, the cram school is doing this.
其實補習班就在做這個事
Now everyone knows that it is said to take a doctoral program and a master's program
現在各位知道說考博士班碩士班
There are tutoring Ken
都有補習肯
And they say there are about three
而且他們說在學校大概有三
Half of the students are admitted to Ph.D. through cram school
一半的學生是經過補習班補習考上博士
why? because the teacher is lazy
為什麼?因為老師很懶
It's his archeology question.
就是他的考古題啊
They also changed
他們也是都變了一下
His question bank is small
他的題庫很小
He also knows, so their students can recite it a little
他也知道 所以他們學生稍微背一下就可以
So let's take care of a concept-related knowledge
所以我們就好好處理一個概念相關知識
sometimes it's not that hard
有的時候沒那麼難
Let's talk about natural language understanding now
我們現在講一下自然語言理解
I just said that it takes a lot of knowledge
剛說要需要非常多的知識
How to acquire this knowledge
那怎麼樣獲取這個知識
this is the most important point
這是最重要的一點
The foundation of natural language understanding is knowledge
自然語言理解的基礎就是知識
Language is the most important power to record knowledge
語言是記錄知識最重要的功率
So learn from the language
所以就是從語言裡面去學習
Language knowledge is divided into two parts
語言知識分成兩部分
one is the rule
一個是規則
For example, a rule of word formation
譬如說一個構詞的規則
What are the sentence patterns? Chinese Grammar
句型是怎麼樣 中文文法
belongs to this
屬於這個
The advantage of this rule is that
這個規則有個好處就是說
Our Chinese is subject verb object
我們中文是主詞 動詞 受詞
This structure is most frequently
這種結構最頻繁
so you swap anything
所以你把任何一個東西抽換
become something else
成另外一個東西的話
Using this rule may be a legitimate argument
用這個規則可能就是一個合法的講法
Although not necessarily meaningful
雖然不見得有意義
That's a lot of imagery experience
那有很多是意象 經驗
For example, the sentence is fluent
譬如文句通順
When you read it, you think this is very logical, right?
你念起來你覺得這個很通順對不對
Chinese medicine, this is even more difficult
文藥 這個就更難
This is more statistical
這個比較偏統計性
So what we just said
所以我們剛講的
remember many patterns
記得很多pattern
Why learn a native speaker
為什麼學一個母語的人
He's not good at grammar
他其實文法不見得好
Let's take the old beauty exam
我們去考老美的那個
He can't pass you in English grammar
英文文法他考不過你
Because we learn English from grammar
因為我們是從文法去學英文
They learned from this ordinary chat
他們是從這個平常聊天學的
So he is the impression
所以他都是印象
he still knows grammar
他還是知道文法
But he doesn't have such a strong sense
但是他沒有那麼強的一個sense
So he is fluent in this aspect
所以他文句通順這方面
he is much stronger than you
他比你強太多
the english book he read
他讀的那個英文書
there may be hundreds of copies
可能有上百本
they have counted
他們有統計過
i.e. a child
就是說一個小孩
American children from childhood to college
美國小孩從小到大學
He learns about ten words a day
他大概一天學十個字
because when he went to college
因為他到大學的時候
Learned more than 300,000 words
學過三十幾萬個字
don't remember
不見得都記得起來
But he really learned so many words
但是他真的是學過那麼多字
So our memory is terrible
所以我們記憶力是非常可怕
The following question is to say
下面的問題就是說
Well, now the machine is also starting from scratch
好,現在機器也是從零開始
How does he learn from so many materials?
他怎麼樣從那麼多的資料裡面去學
then you can learn
然後可以學到
what kind of degree
一個什麼樣的程度
We say that the most abundant textual information on the Internet
我們說網路上最豐富的文字資料
Boundless language, semantic knowledge is indistinguishable from the text
無窮境的語言 語意知識都在文字中一覽無異
This is for people to see
這個是給人看的
So in human terms you probably
所以就人而言的話你大概
We are now reading slowly because of reading
我們現在是因為讀書讀得慢
Otherwise we can gain a lot of knowledge
要不然的話我們可以獲得非常多的知識
Then as far as the machine is concerned these are symbols
然後就機器而言這些都是符號
Like the word Chen Shi
像陳時這兩個字
and cuteness are two symbols
跟可愛都是兩個符號
where is the meaning
那個意義在哪裡
this is very difficult
這個非常難
If you find that it uses ham try
如果發覺說其中用含的嘗試
These are very challenging questions
這些是非常挑戰性的問題
Google everyone knows
Google各位知道說
The recent Google translation is much better than before
最近的Google翻譯比以前要進步很多
Just thanks to Deep Learning
就是拜Deep Learning
is the new machine learning of deep learning
就是深度學習的新的機器學習
But the principle of its translation is
但它的翻譯的原則就是
Rely on many bilingual parallel intonations
仰賴很多雙語的平行語調
For example, we now have many
就譬如說我們現在有很多
Chinese to English
中文翻成英文的
Or translate English into Chinese
或者英文翻成中文的
We have a lot of semantic information
這個我們很多的語意的資訊
Already included in this translation
已經用含在這個翻譯裡面
so it goes to see
所以它去看
memorize this translation
這個翻譯背起來
Didn't I just talk about the phonetic conversion?
剛才我不是講說那個音轉字
You go to memorize that Windows
你去背那個一個Windows
If you finish memorizing the seven characters in rhyme
七個字交韻字背完了的話
your ability is very strong
你的能力就非常強
a little harder to translate
翻譯稍微難一點
because it has an order that changes
是因為它有的次序會變
So most if the order remains the same
所以大部分如果次序不變
It actually flips pretty well
它其實翻的都還不錯
That first Google translation
那最早的Google翻譯
actually simpler
其實更簡單
Not using Deep Learning
不是用Deep Learning
It is an Algorithm written by one person
它是一個人寫的Algorithm
Because at that time the key point of the translation was to say
因為那時候翻譯一個重點是說
It has about 30 languages ​​in the world
它有大概世界上30幾個語言
There are always people who need to turn over and over again.
都是經常有人需要翻來翻去的
Of course, the translation to English is the most frequent
當然翻到英文最頻繁
Then these 30 languages
那這30幾個語言
Both have information about the counterpart in English
都有跟英文對方的資料
So there's a lot of these data out there
所以有非常多這些資料存在
So this guy wrote an Algorithm
所以這個人就寫了一個Algorithm
How to use statistical methods for translation
怎麼去用統計方法做翻譯
don't understand at all
完全不懂
Just use statistics to find out
就用統計可以翻出來
After the translation, there are 35 languages
那翻完以後是35個語言
translated into 35 languages
翻成35個語言
all can each other
全部都可以對方
very fast
非常快
whether it is good or not is another matter
好不好是另外一回事
It's doing better now
現在是做得比較好一點
So learning the language of these online
所以在學習這些網路上的語言
There are two ways
有兩種方法
One is Rule Base
一個是Rule Base
In the early stage, before 1990, the Rule Base model was the main model.
早期大概1990年以前都是以Rule Base法則式模型為主
different knowledge
對不同的知識
First divide it into clusters and categories
先把它分 cluster 分門別類
Then write the relevant rules for each class
然後每一類撰寫相關的規則
The same class is more like and easier to write
同一類就比較像比較容易寫
The advantage is that its true or false examples are relatively easy to figure out why
優點是它的正確或錯誤例子比較容易找出原因
As we did knowledge law the earliest
像我們做知識法最早
At that time also Rule Base
那個時候也是Rule Base
So when it's wrong you can know right away why
所以它錯的時候馬上可以知道為什麼
The system is more stable
這個系統穩定性比較高
easy to handle this particular case
容易處理這個特別的case
Then suitable for inference operations
然後適合進行推理運算
Almost all large-scale systems in the industry are Rule Base
那工業界的大型系統幾乎都是Rule Base
because you are in industry
因為你在工業界
you make a system
你做一個系統出來
you tell the boss this
你跟老闆說這個
this is wrong
這個錯了
If you know your mistakes, you can make amends
知錯能改不會要過對不對
It will be corrected tomorrow
明天就要改對
Rule BaseDo it
Rule Base做到
if you do it in another way
你如果用別的方法做
The disadvantage is that the rules are written by humans, which is very labor-intensive
缺點呢,規則是由人戰寫,非常耗費人力
The subjective consciousness of different people is very different, and the rules of writing will conflict
不同的人主觀意識差異很大,寫的規則會衝突
And people can cover a limited range
而且人可以涵蓋範圍有限
All of us have a teacher Su Keyi, he does machine translation
我們所有一位蘇克宜老師,他做機器翻譯
He is really doing it, he used to run a company outside
他是真的在做,以前他在外面開公司的
His machine translation first used Rubber Bass
他這個機器翻譯最早是用Rubber Bass
Encountered a problem, the first
碰到一個問題,裡面第一個
He hired quite a few linguists and often quarreled
他聘得蠻多語言學家,經常吵架
He said I made him right, and you made him bad, you write one, you talk about me
他說我把他做對,你又把他做壞,你寫一個,你講到我
What about this?
那這怎麼辦?
He later said that he fires a linguist every time
他後來講說他每次就Fire一個語言學家
He improves accuracy
他準確都就提高
He said that it is best for a company to be written by one person, and there will be no quarrel
他說最好一個公司就一個人寫就好了,這不會吵架
Well, there are some companies now
那真的現在是有一些公司
His general manager is his earliest Founder is a weak person
他的總經理就是他最早的Founder是顯弱的人
He said I would never be FIRE
他說我永遠不會被人家FIRE
Because if he leaves, his company will collapse
因為他一走的話,他的公司就垮了
conflicts between rules
規則之間容易產生衝突
Like Microsoft they are doing Cortena
像微軟他們在做Cortena
The same goes for voice assistants
語音助理也是一樣
he can answer questions
他是可以回答問題的
He's doing about 12 fields now
他現在做了大概有12個領域
Traveling, what about ordering food?
旅遊啊,什麼訂餐啊
or this
或者是這個
Meteorology, and constellations
氣象啊,還有星座這些東西
But every time he wants to add a new field, it will be troublesome
但是他每次要加一個新的領域就麻煩
Because of this new field added problems
因為這新的領域加的問題
knowledge
知識啊
will conflict with the previous
會跟以前的衝突
So he will steal other people's problems
所以他會把人家的問題搶來
It's very troublesome to grab and grab
再搶來搶去很麻煩
So this is if being the biggest problem
所以這個是如果被是最大的問題
then let me give an example
那我舉一個例子
This is difficult to standardize in English literature
這是英文文獻難為標準
That is to say, you are behind the English paper
就是說你在英文的paper後面
There are references
都有reference
Inside the author and title journal, one is drawn out
裡面的作者和title期刊,一個抽出來
This is followed by Volume issue, Pace number
這後面是Volume issue,Pace number
To extract one, you have to write a lot of rules
要一個抽出來,你要寫一大堆規則
sorry, drink some water
抱歉,喝點水
it's exactly an hour
現在正好一個鐘頭
Then the first Rule means that the Volume needs to be shaved, and Esho will shave again.
那這個第一個Rule,就是說Volume後面要刮鬍,Esho再來刮鬍
All good, write one every time you encounter a different situation
都好,每次碰到一個不同情形就寫一個
OK, this is the basic Rule. After Volume, you need to vaccinate and shave, then come to Esho, and then come to something
OK,這個就是基本的Rule,Volume後面要接種刮鬍,再來Esho,再來什麼東西
it is written as a rule
它就寫成一個規則
The parameter is also different for active learning, it uses the plot rate or the gold-like network to learn
參數是積極學也不一樣,它用積率或類成金網路來學
The current mainstream language processing technology is these two
目前的語言處理主流技術就是這兩種
It mainly replaces this problem with a mathematical optimization problem
它主要是把這個問題都換成一個數學上面的最優化的問題
Optimization is having an objective with a number of
最優化就是有一個目標含數
Then you input this one input later
然後你把這個一個input輸進去以後
it is right and wrong it can learn
它是正確還錯誤它就可以學習
Statistical models need to do a lot of feature engineering
統計模型需要做很多feature engineering
But for deep learning it is less necessary
但深入學習它比較不需要
But it needs a lot of data to train
但它要訓練的資料非常多
In fact, most deep learning
其實大部分的深入學習
probably in the company
大概在公司
Only big companies can do well
大的公司才有辦法做得好
This is known as a high degree of automation
這個號稱是自動化程度高
In fact, the preparation of the previous materials is very labor-intensive.
其實前面資料準備功夫非常大
It didn't mention this
這個它沒有去提
The disadvantage is that these three shortcomings are probably difficult for ordinary companies to accept
缺點是這三個缺點大概一般公司很難接受
results are unpredictable
結果是難以預測
Let's say you added some new training knowledge
就說你加了一些新的訓練的知識
it might be wrong with some old ones
它可能就會有一些舊的會錯
it has no way of explaining why it's good
它沒有辦法解釋為什麼不錯
If we know our mistakes, we can correct them
知錯我們講能改
it is hard to change
它是難改
Why do many big companies not change
為什麼很多大公司不改
he is willing to use
他願意用
So he usually treats those with higher frequency
所以他通常對出現頻率比較高的那些
relatively high accuracy
準確度比較高
otherwise lower
要不然就比較低
So there are some special cases that he can't handle at all.
所以有些特例他根本沒辦法處理
long distance relationship
長距離的關係
Those are relatively low frequency
那些都是頻率比較低的
is also difficult to deal with
也是很難處理
the hardest thing is to say
最難的就是說
He has a bottleneck in accuracy
他準確率有一個瓶頸
He can't make it up to more than one level
他做到一個程度以上上不去
Because you have a lot of very detailed knowledge, he can't use it
因為你很多很細的知識他用不上
So we draw a very simple graph
所以我們畫一個很簡單的圖
Parametric machine learning is a black box job
就是參數式機器學習是一個黑箱作業
So he has a window to see the kitchen
所以他這個廚房是有窗子看不到
Then the back of the entrance is where you can see what he does.
那這個入口背是可以看到他怎麼做
be more at ease
比較放心一點
Glassbox
Glassbox
Let's show you now
那我們現在給各位看一下
Some examples of deep learning used in machine translation
深度學習用在機器翻譯上一些例子
Even he doesn't talk about understanding
就是他也是不談理解
He just made the translation as good as he thought it would be
他只是把這個翻譯做到他認為最好的一個程度
But this so-called best has a frequency standard
但這個所謂最好有一個頻量的標準
not for ordinary people
不是一般的人看的
This is a translator to understand personnel
這是一個翻譯要了解人事
what do you think, with considerable difficulty
是怎麼想,有相當大的困難
This English is better, you can see
這個英文好一點,可以看出來
這個不 make sense to understand how people want to have considerable difficulty
這個不 make sense to understand how people want to have considerable difficulty
just don't write anything, right?
就不要寫什麼東西對不對
That's a better way
那這個是比較好的方法
to understand how people think is very difficult
to understand how people think is very difficult
Then below is I ask my secretary to take down the telephone number
然後下面是 I ask my secretary to take down the telephone number
I asked my secretary and took down the phone number
我問我的秘書,記下的電話號碼
This is a mistake, not to ask the secretary
這翻錯了,不是問秘書
Good translation is I ask the secretary to take down this phone number
好的翻譯是我請秘書記下這個電話號碼
So his, in fact, turned over with a plan and a concession
所以他那個,其實翻了有謀有讓
Most of this is true, but because he doesn't understand
這大部分都對了,但是他因為不懂
So those words together don't make sense
所以那個話連起來,不 make sense
再來說 I ask my secretary to take down the letter
再來說 I ask my secretary to take down the letter
This is to test him on purpose, he will definitely not
這個是故意考他,他一定不會的
i asked my secretary to take the letter
我問我的秘書,拿走信
In fact, he means in Chinese that I dictate this letter and ask the secretary to write it down
其實他中文的意思是我口述這封信,請秘書寫下
This is the correct English meaning
這個是正確的英文的意思
下面是Big Trucks are forbidden in this road to make room for small cars
下面是Big Trucks are forbidden in this road to make room for small cars
Big trucks banned on this road to make room for smaller cars
大卡車禁止在這條路上為小汽車騰出空間
Is there any reference value for him?
就是他有沒有參考價值
Probably not even reference value
大概連參考價值都沒有
Generally speaking, there is a reference value, and if I miss a word or two, I will correct it, right?
一般說有參考價值說錯一兩個字我改一下對不對
If he has to rewrite this, he doesn't need to rewrite it at all.
他這個有要重寫的話就根本不需要他翻了
A better translation is that big trucks are not allowed on this road and small cars are allowed to pass
比較好的翻譯是大卡車不准上這條路一邊小型汽車通行
This is more like people
這個是比較像人家
If you understand this sentence, it's okay if you don't speak fluently.
如果你懂了這句話你講的不太通順還可以
But sometimes you mean the wrong thing
但是有的時候你意思是講錯
If you don't understand English today and you need to translate it, it will be very troublesome
如果今天不懂英文要你靠你來翻譯的話就很麻煩
So we use the following example to talk about unified self-selection
所以我們用這個下面例子來講說統一自選去
Taipei is a child smuggled
台北是一位小孩走私了
I’ve read it today, don’t read the following, you’ll probably understand it right away
我今天念過去了你不要看下面你大概都馬上了解
But in fact there are many words below
但事實上下面有很多詞
I'm omitting the part of the word now, just the word
我現在把單字的部分省略光是詞
Taipei City Taipei City one by one
台北市台北市一位一位一位
There are many possibilities, right?
有很多的可能性對不對
But there is only one meaningful combination
但有意義的組合只有一種
And what you are hearing is the 11 children in Taipei
而且各位聽到的就是台北11位小孩子
the part that is red
是紅色的這一部分
I didn't hear anything else
其他都沒聽到
Actually not heard
事實上不是沒聽到
You are the same master as Xia Qi
你跟夏綺那個大師是一樣的
You are 99% enumerated by you
你99%都被你enumered
You quickly find out that doesn't work
你很快就發現那個不 work
So his homophonic choice
所以他的同音之選擇
That is, each one is an input sound
就是每一個都是輸入的一個音
Then there are single-character and two-character words below
然後下面有單字二字詞
he doesn't know which one you want to choose
他不知道你要選哪一個
So you use a mathematical model to calculate
所以你用一個數學的model來計算
In the end you may choose the yellow one
最後你可能選黃色的這個
not necessarily right
不見得是對的
Then it depends on whether your mathematical model is well written.
那就看你的那個數學model寫得好不好
Now let's see where the difficulty of this problem lies.
那我們現在看一下這個問題的難度在哪裡
the pattern recognition
the pattern recognition
On the choice of homophonic system
就同音制的選擇
I hit one
我打一個
The phonetic book in Taiwan also needs to be toned
在台灣的註音書還需要打聲調
right
對不對
Then I just talked about five to fifteen unisons
那我剛講五到十五個同音制
The mainland is silent
大陸是不打聲調
the one it triples
它三倍的那個
Three times as many words is fifteen to forty-five word possibilities
三倍多的字就是十五到四十五個字的可能性
so this is the doctor
所以這就是醫師
All Physicians Gotta Get It All Right
所有的醫師要把它全部做對
very many homophones and words
非常多的同音制和詞
It is not necessarily a statement, some are homonyms
它不見得是陳詞,有的是同音制
There are still a lot of grabbing words, and the grabbing words are next to it
那還有很多搶詞,搶詞就旁邊的
Like this is the lion, sent to the hospital, the market, what kind of toothpaste
像這個是獅中,送醫,市場,什麼牙膏
So when you beat the doctor down
所以你把這個醫師打下來的時候
You have to do it right, not him right, everything next to him has to be right
你要把它做對,不是他對,他旁邊的全部都要對
a whole bunch of restrictions like this
一大堆這種限制
So we just said that the seven-character Window can be memorized like this
所以我們剛剛講說,那個七個字的Window這樣背起來
It's possible to solve this problem
居然就可以把這個問題解決是
It's a pity that we humans are not very creative in speech
可惜我們人講話是不太有創造力
Everything we say is written into a certain paragraph of text.
我們講的話都被人家寫到某一段文字裡面去
Let me give you an example to show you the homonym context
那選舉同音制上下文,我舉個例子來給各位看
We used to do smart calligraphy as well
以前我們做智能書法也是一樣
dermatology, so we'll write
皮膚科,所以我們就會寫說
If the front is dermatology, internal medicine, cancer
如果前面是什麼皮膚科,內科,什麼癌症
The latter subject is river fighting, right?
後面這科就是河斗科對不對
Then the doctor's words are Muge Branch
然後科醫師的話就是木葛科
if there is an after
如果後面有一個之後
bump into dermatology
碰到皮膚科
If you are a nuclear medicine doctor, the two should be discussed together
如果是核酷科醫師的話,那兩個一講
This nuclear cool medical score is a little higher than his
這個核酷科醫分數要比他高一點
But if I say the following, you will be miserable
但是如果我下面這句話你就慘了
To treat this kind of allergic skin, physicians only have experience
治療這種過敏性皮膚,科醫師只有經驗
This is the saying, if you don’t know how to do it, you will do it wrong
就是這句話你如果不了解怎麼做的做不對
You just use points, one high and one low, you will definitely not be able to do it
你光是用分數,這個一高一低,一定做不出來的
Because there are tens of thousands of my way of speaking, it is impossible to do it right
因為我這種講法有千千萬萬無數的,不可能做對
So we now propose that what we just talked about is that
所以我們現在提出剛剛講的是說
What others have done, we now propose a way
別人的做法,我們現在提出一個做法
We believe it is a very simple one
我們相信是一個非常簡單的一個做法
And that's what I just said about using Pattern Recognition
而且就是我剛剛講用Pattern Recognition的做法
Pattern Recognition, we think that language learning is basically Pattern Matching
Pattern Recognition,我們認為學習語言基本上就是Pattern Matching
When people see the difference between machines, they will generate it when they learn
人看機器差別是人學的時候會把它generate
More abstract Patterns will be remembered
比較抽象的Pattern會記起來
In this way, if I learn one sentence, I may be able to watch many dramas and understand many sentences
這樣的話我學一個句子,我可能就可以看很多劇,了解很多句子
Like this below, Hon Hai Foxconn Technology Group
像這個下面是,鴻海富士康科技集團
Shenzhen division of labor, this is just an organization name
深圳分工師,這只是一個機構名稱
will produce smart machines
將生產智慧型機器
If I knew it was an institution when I read it
我如果一讀就知道它是機構的話
This sentence is very simple, isn't it?
這個句子很簡單,對不對?
This is followed by the name of a gene
這個後面是一個基因的名稱
incase tumor necrosis factor receptor
incase tumor necrosis factor receptor
partner factor
socia factor
The words of this man who doesn't understand life
這個不懂生活的人的話
Absolutely impossible to know that this is a gene
絕對不可能知道這個是一個基因
Now it's time to teach the computer to read all this
現在要教電腦把這些都讀懂
How much knowledge is needed
要多少知識
The following is the relationship extraction
下面是關係抽取
Like MIRNA induced atopsis targeting BCl2
像是MIRNA induced atopsis targeting BCl2
Only biological people can't read this
這只有生物的人讀不懂
Now we ask the computer to say
現在我們要求電腦就是說
it needs to be able
它要能夠
It used to be said that a computer should be able to operate in a very harsh environment
以前說電腦要能夠在很惡劣的環境
nothing to be afraid of going swimming
去游泳什麼不怕
Now that's bad too
現在這也是很惡劣
It's just that most of the creatures can't read.
就是這個生物大部分都讀不懂
to be able to read him
要能夠把他讀懂
Then extract the relation
然後把relation抽出來
question category
問題分類
like does anyone know
像有沒有人知道
This fragrant tree duck restaurant in Tainan
這家位在台南的香樹鴨餐廳
This is our test robot
這個是我們考試的考機器人
will you understand
會不會懂
What are the must-eat foods in Taipei?
去台北有哪幾樣一定要吃的美食呢
near MRT station
靠近捷運站
will you understand
會不會聽得懂
I can't understand now
現在都聽不懂
There are many other patterns
還有很多其他的pattern
let's see now
那我們現在看一下
Our present model is
我們現在提出的模型是
We used to have a dream
這我們以前有個dream
It is pattern matching
就是pattern matching
if
如果
The first rule is written by the machine itself
第一個規則是機器自己寫
And it's flexible when it's right
而且對的時候很flexible
Is it possible to apply a rule we just talked about to be
是否可以將剛才我們講的一個法則是
One is the Impressionist Statistical
一個是印象派的統計式
Both models kind of all fit together
兩種模型有點全部都合在一起
high automation
就是滿足高度自動化
Accuracy is highly interpretable
準確度高度容易解釋
easy to explain is important
容易解釋很重要
Let us now look at the phenomenon of language
我們現在看一下語言的現象
what kind of
有一些什麼樣的
In fact, everyone knows
其實大家都知道
Is the spelling checker in English correct?
英文的spelling checker對不對
It's because you mistyped an English word
就是你打錯一個英文字
he immediately
他馬上
especially now on mobile
尤其現在在手機上
all playing
全部在打
Wrong two and he'll correct you, right?
錯於兩個他會把你糾正過來對不對
So this Jinshi comparison actually existed very early.
所以這個進士比對其實很早就有
is there a way to replace this
有沒有辦法把這個換
It's just what I said, happy three, happy four, or some more boring words
就是我講的話,樂三樂四的,或者多一些很無聊的字
Now we humans will not be affected at all, we can all understand
我們現在人是完全不會受影響,都聽得懂
Like when we do voice input, there are many RRRs in the middle
像我們做語音輸入的時候,中間有很多RRR那些
We can automatically tune these sounds of the drum position, as if we heard them or not
鼓位的這些音,我們都可以自動律調,好像聽到沒聽到一樣
What we do now is actually the same as printing me with this word
我們現在做法其實就跟這個字印我一樣
Automatically group these patterns with similarities and differences, and then find a representative
把這些大同小異的pattern自動分群,然後找一個代表
Use these representatives to compare
用這些代表來比對
This we call the principle-based approach
這個我們稱作principle-based approach
Already applying for a patent
已經在申請專利了
Then this principle-based approach only needs to use a small number of principles
那這principle-based approach只要用少數的principle
This principle is a bit like RRR, but its advantage is that it is automatically written
這principle跟RRR有點像,但它的好處是自動寫的
And its match comparison is very flexible
而且它的match比對是非常flexible
Let's use a few examples to see the power of using this principle-match
我們用幾個例子來看看使用這個principle-match的power
Like Chinese addresses, we used to write rules to ensure that
像中文地址,以前我們在寫規則,要保證
If I want to make a computer software now
我現在如果要做一個電腦軟體
Mark all the addresses written on the Internet
把網路上所有寫的地址全部標出來
how much effort it takes
要花多少力氣
He skipped this one, sorry
他這個跳過去了,抱歉
OK, I'll skip this paragraph first
OK,我先把這一段跳掉
It is the number of this pattern of the address
就是地址的這個pattern有多少
Generally, when you go out to write the mutual gathering address, this is probably how you write it.
一般各位出去寫互聚地址的大概就是這樣寫
Shidaan District, Taipei, Shidaan District, Central East, right?
台北的士大安區,中央東的士大安區是吧
not revealing
一個不露
But we know that addresses are often not
但是我們知道地址常常是沒有像弄
no write zone
也沒有寫區的
So this time you may have another address like this
所以這個時候你可能有另外一個地址是這樣
Sometimes you will add another Dongyang East Taxi No. 17 Shidaan in the center of Taipei
有的時候你會又加了一個台北市中心的東央東的士大安17號
This plus these things is very harmful to the weak quilt
這個加上去這些東西對弱被子傷害力非常大
Because it is written behind it, it must be connected to the road or connected to the area
因為它後面寫的,是後面一定是接路或者接區
then you are not at all
那你這個完全不是
so you hook this thing up
所以你接上這個東西完蛋
But speaking from someone who has tried it, this is not a problem at all
但是以這個有嘗試的人講,這個完全不是問題
One point is that it is the same as the R2 we mentioned, it will turn green immediately
一點就是跟我們講那個R2一樣,馬上就綠掉
So now when we make a computer, we must be able to put these things that should be placed or can be omitted.
所以現在我們做一個電腦就要能夠把這些該放的或可以省略的
all can be learned
全部都能夠學下
Like ours, we know it by means of statistics
像我們這個就是用統計的方式就知道
So now the rules we wrote in the past probably need thirty or forty rules.
所以現在最後以前我們寫的規則大概地址要三四十個規則
Because I don't know if you start from Taipei or from Da'an District
因為我不知道你是從台北開始還是從大安區開始
Then I don't know if you end up with number or None or something
那我不知道你結束在號還是None什麼東西
So write a bunch of rules
所以要寫一大堆規則
Now only one Pattern is needed to calculate all the additions and subtractions
現在只需要一個Pattern就可以把所有這些該加該減的全部都算進去
Then this is the best speech recognition test
那這個也是一個最好的語音辨識的測試
You can't say Google Siri right now
你現在去念Google Siri這個一定不會對
That is to say, it mainly pairs the word with the noun that follows it.
就是說它主要是要把這個字和那個後面的名詞配對
Flowers should be matched with this wooden signature, and signatures should be matched with this word
花要配這個木頭的籤 簽名要配這個字
So here I used to do natural calligraphy because I spent a lot of effort to get it right
那這裡面我以前在做自然書法是花了九牛二虎之力把它做對
It's very hard to write, I don't know how many bettors
非常辛苦 寫的不知道多少貝者
Then once this academician came to test
然後有一次這個院士來測試
This academician is very smart, he added a posture after the posture
這院士很聰明 他把姿勢後面加了一個姿
Immediately the system is all wrong
馬上系統就全錯
Another academician made him cute and pottery
另外一個院士把他加的可愛又陶氣
A very pompous approach
非常陶氣的一個做法
So these systems are written cleanly
所以這些系統都寫得很乾淨
It is connected to this behind the bathing pool, connected to this
就是洗澡池後面接這個 接這個
can't just add
不能隨便再加
Delation I don’t want all the cute ones
Delation 全部都可愛的也不要
Don't do anything, see if you're right
什麼都不要 看你會不會對
Now we basically know all of these
現在我們基本上這些全部都會對
We now only need to write a Pattern
我們現在只要寫一個Pattern
Digit Quantity Agit
Digit Quantity Agit
Because we already know that these other added Janes
因為我們就知道其他這些加的簡
It's the same as those addresses just now
就是跟剛才那些地址一樣
Your noun bath pool you can write two or three
你名詞 洗澡池你可以寫兩個 三個
Write something very cute on the front
前面寫非常可愛的什麼東西
whatever you write will be right
隨便你寫都會對
So it only has one Pattern and it will all be solved for you
所以它只有一個Pattern就全部為你解決
A lot of English literature we just talked about
剛才我們講的英文文獻寫的一大堆
It happens that writing a thousand rules is not enough
發生在寫一千的規則也不夠
Everyone knows English literature on the Internet
各位知道網路上的英文的文獻
it has the standard wording
它有標準的寫法
the same document
同一個文獻
you can write it in many different ways
你可以有很多不同的寫法
Can you guess how many spellings there are?
大家可以猜得出來有大概多少寫法嗎?
i will give you a number now
我現在給你一個數字
Raise your hand if you think the approximate number is correct
大概的數字你認為是對的話舉手
100 different spellings
100個不同寫法
like this are different ways of writing
像這種都是不同寫法
What is the cap number and the bean number is written differently
帽號什麼豆號不同寫法
Raise your hand if you guess 100
猜100個的請舉手
1000's
1000個的
good 5000
好 5000
strangeness
奇怪
How many people think the rest
剩下的人數認為多少
10,000
1萬的
OK thank you
OK 好 謝謝
The answer is more than 8600
答案是8600多種
Just such a simple document
就這麼簡單的一個文獻
More than 8600 kinds
8600多種
So if you're going to learn
所以你要去學的話
this will be dead
這會被死
Our current approach is very simple, just write a lot of rules here, so a thousand is not enough, right?
我們現在做法很簡單,就把這邊寫一大堆規則,所以一千個不夠,對不對?
We are very simple now, we know what can be connected behind this volume 38,
我們現在很簡單就是,我們知道這個volume 38後面可以接什麼東西,
You can pick up something on the left side of the issue and memorize it. This can be done with statistics, and there is no need for that person to take care of it.
issue左邊可以接什麼東西,把它背起來,這用統計做就好了,不需要那個人去管,
The same is true, issue and page number, what can be added in the middle, remember it with statistics,
這也是一樣,issue和page number,中間可以加什麼東西,這個用統計把它記起來,
Then we only have one pattern, which is VIP, volume issue, and page number, and include all of these,
然後我們只有一個pattern,就是VIP,volume issue,page number,就把所有的這些全部都包含進去,
This method is also the same, just like the address just now, because I am the same, a principle,
這個做法也是一樣,跟剛才的地址,因為我一樣,一個principle,
Let's compare the error rate with the best active learning, CRF, because the accuracy is already very high,
我們去跟最好的積極學習,CRF來比,錯誤率,因為這個準確度已經非常高,
So in reverse, our error is 0.5, which is 99.5% right,
所以是反過來,我們的錯誤是0.5,就是99.5%是對,
That's a little better, it's 98.8%, the page here is much better, what are these, standard learning,
那比較好一點,它是98.8%,在這個地方page比較好很多,這些是什麼,標準的學習,
Two thousand articles to test
兩千篇來測試
there are other testing agencies
那還有其他測試社
Our performance at each testing agency
我們在每個測試社的表現
Performance is almost the same
Performance都差不多
The last level is actually the hardest
那到最後一關其實是最難
It's called FreeStar
這是所謂的FreeStar
FreeStar what
FreeStar什麼
Many researchers from our Academia Sinica
就把我們中研院的很多研究員
The book that was written after him wrote down
寫在他後面的那個著作寫下來
Because when our researchers wrote
因為我們的研究員寫的時候
They all miss three and miss four, right?
都漏三漏四的對不對
then that
然後那個
He can understand you can understand
他看得懂你也看得懂
But the computer can't understand
但是電腦看不懂
So you go to use this more formal study
所以你去用這個比較正規的學習
He is very wrong
他就錯誤力非常高
Error force fast to 10
錯誤力快到10
OSA is approaching 10
OSA快到10
TITLE is 28.9
TITLE是28.9
Journal and everything are messed up
Journal什麼的都一塌糊塗
After he has learned the standard
他在標準的上面學完以後
Run these tests in general
跑到一般的這些測試
But our system basically handles very high
但是我們的系統基本上容處理很高
It's almost as accurate as the original
它的準確度幾乎跟原來是一模一樣
So this way
所以就是說這種做法
Like what's in Taipei Social Home Center
就像台北社會家中心的什麼
I don't care if you join me or not
你加不加我都無所謂
It's easy to learn a lot
它很容易就把很多東西學會
then this can
那這個可以
Everyone, just say anything
各位隨便講任何一個東西
I can show you thirty or forty possibilities
我都可以照三四十個可能性給各位看
The distance between the two places is from Taipei to Kaohsiung
兩地距離從台北到高雄
say 360 kilometers
比如說360公里
360 kilometers from Taipei to Kaohsiung
至台北距離高雄有360公里
Or 360 kilometers from Taipei to Kaohsiung
或者是台北到高雄360公里
do not write yes ah do not write what
不寫有啊不寫什麼
How many kilometers is the distance between Taipei and Kaohsiung?
台北高雄之間距離不少於多少公里
actually mean the same thing
其實都是同樣意思
then if you are
那你如果是
Go online and answer these questions
去網路上回答這些問題啊
it is written slightly differently
它稍微有一不同寫法
You're going to write the rules, you can't finish
你就要去寫規則是寫不完
So our final conclusion is that
所以我們最後得到的結論就是
It's just P1
它這裡面就P1
The first location, the second location and the description of the distance
第一個地點第二個地點還有距離的描述的
The distance between images and the distance value
像之間的距離還有距離值
These few will never change
這幾個是一定不變
It doesn't matter if it can be mapped or deleted
其他可以影射或delete都沒有關係
The second way of writing is that you write the distance in the middle
那第二個寫法就是你把距離寫在中間
Probably only these two patterns
大概就只有這兩個pattern
describe all the relationships
就把這所有的關係都描述清楚
For example, when we actually do it, put this Pattern
舉例說我們實際在做的時候把這個Pattern
Can automatically Summarize out
能夠自動Summarize出來
It's not written by humans, it's written by computers
也不是人寫的,這是電腦寫的
Then it is very easy to compare
然後它比對的時候就非常的輕鬆
So let's now look at the smart agent application
所以我們現在看一下智慧型代理應用
12 minutes left
現在還有12分鐘
Talk about some of the more important applications of this
講到一些比較重要的這個應用
Smart Classification System
智慧型分類系統
Now our mail
現在我們的郵件
Emails you have received
各位收到的郵件
Usually we do that in Zhongyuanyuan
通常我們在中原院都會做那個
or on Google
或者在Google
will remove SpamMail first
都會把SpamMail先把它移除
Then SpamMail has many methods of Detect
那SpamMail有很多這種Detect的方法
But I usually pick up the phone or
但是我平常拿起手機還是
I didn't read it for a while and wrote 100 new letters
一陣子不看它又寫了100封新的
I can't accept it, right?
收不了對不對
What is the email system we want?
我們希望的Email系統是什麼呢?
It can put this important and urgent Email at the top
它可以把這個重要又急的Email放最前面
For example, there are five
比如說有五封
For example, the vice president's office called you
比如說副院長辦公室打電話找你
This is very important
這個很重要
this is one of them
這是one of them
So if the computer reads it, it will be placed in the five envelopes immediately.
所以電腦如果看完它馬上就放在那五封裡面
that's enough for me
這樣的話就滿足我
I'm short on time
我現在時間很短
I can only read a few
我只能看幾封
I saw those five
我就看到那五封
can be dealt with immediately
馬上就可以處理
down may be a second tier
下來可能是第二個層
third floor fourth floor
第三層 第四層
it can follow these
它可以依照這些
your own way
你自己規定的方式
Categorize this email
把這個email分類
must go at this time
這個時候就一定要去
read that email content
讀那個email內容
understand
讀懂
After understanding to a certain extent
懂到一個程度以後
There is no way to classify
才有辦法分類
There is also this automatic off-script recovery
還有這個自動離稿恢復
There are many emails
這有很多email
For example, ask you when
譬如說問你什麼時候
What kind of meeting can I have?
可以開什麼會
wrote a lot
寫了一大堆
Finally there is a table
最後有一個表
let you lick right
讓你舔對不對
then you already have one
那你已經有一個
Google's calendar is over there
Google的calendar在那邊
You are Google Calendar
你就Google Calendar
are you going to find it yourself?
自己去找嘛
Just tell the computer to find it yourself
就跟電腦說你自己去找
See if I have time
看我有空時間
just fill it back
就自己填回去
so later these
所以以後這些
is the appointment
就是appointment
It's just things like fixed grains.
就是定形式粒這些東西
can be automatically read by computer
都可以由電腦自動讀
Automatic recovery
自動恢復
don't need a secretary
也不需要秘書做
This one is more difficult
這個下面比較難
automated scoring system
自動評分系統
Ministry of Science and Technology Program
科技部計畫
Ministry of Science and Technology is now a year
科技部現在一年
There may be hundreds of thousands of plans
可能有幾十萬個計畫
go in
進去
This suggestion is not from me, but from the Executive Yuan
這個建議不是我講的,是行政院的那個什麼
A certain official said, he said it cost too much money
某一個官員講,他說這個花太多錢
Send a plan every time
每一次送一個計畫
A plan needs to be sent to three people for review
一個計畫大概要送三個人審核
2000 yuan per person
一個人是兩千塊
So a plan is six thousand
所以一個計畫就是六千塊
Those hundreds of thousands of projects add up to billions
那幾十萬個計畫算起來是上幾十億
This is the first trial and the deputy judge has not yet arrived. The deputy judge is
這是初審還沒有到副審,副審是
It was also sent to some more famous scholars for review
又送給一些比較有名的學者在審
Is there any way for this to be like TOEFL composition?
這個都有沒有辦法像托福的作文一樣
automatic scoring
自動打分數
TOEFL Essay Now Has Two Scores
托福作文現在有兩個分數
One is a human call, the other is a computer call
一個是人打,一個是電腦打
computer, because it is roughly divided into six levels
電腦打,因為它大概分六個層次
six levels, it has had a lot of examples before
六個層次,它以前已經有非常多的例子
What kind of composition is at which level
什麼樣的作文是在哪一個層次
So now the computer can do a classification
所以現在電腦可以做一個分類
It's a new composition
就是新的作文來
It puts you in the most likely tier
它就把你分到最可能的那一層
score decides
分數就決定了
If this score is similar to that of others
如果這個分數跟人打的差不多的話
it's over
它這個就過關了
it saves a lot of effort
它就省了很多力氣
about three percent
大概百分之三
95% of the cases are passed
95%的case都過關
There are a few 5% cases
有少數5%的case
If the scores are too far apart
如果分數差太遠
find someone else to fight
再找一個人打
Just save Raleigh
就省羅利奇
So the Ministry of Science and Technology plans to do the same?
所以科技部計畫是不是也可以這樣
province alone
一個人省
Then a computer saves
然後一個電腦省
then the score is very close
然後分數很接近
Just pass
就過關
How many billions of dollars can this save the country?
這可以省國家多少億的錢
Then the essay province
然後論文省
Papers we are now saving
我們現在省的論文
Like all of our resources in a journal
像我們在資源所有一個期刊
English periodicals
英文期刊
1,000 papers submitted each year
一年有1000篇paper投來
In the end less than 5% were accepted
最後只有不到5%的被接受
95% were rejected
就95%被reject
Nor can the computer be used for a preliminary review
也不能把電腦做一個最初步的審核
Don't even look at the 50%
說這50%根本不要看
you can reject
就可以reject
Write a very simple English is not fluent
寫一個很簡單的英文不通順
or what kind of case
或者是什麼樣的案
He can read this
這個他都可以讀得出來
resume selection
履歷選擇
Now we have trouble finding a job
現在我們找工作也很麻煩
resume to which company
履歷投到那個公司
The company picks up
公司一接
Like that big company, there are tens of thousands of letters
像那個大公司一來就是上萬封
he can't read
他沒辦法讀
He wants to say there is a form
他希望說有個表格
Then he uses that data base for everything
然後他就所有東西都用那個data base來處理
But most people don't like that
但一般人不喜歡這樣
OK, what about the rating systems?
好,這些評分系的以後呢
most can use computer
大部分都可以用電腦
The same is true for recommendation systems, product recommendation
推薦系統也是一樣,商品推薦
Now you want to buy an air conditioner
現在你要買一個冷氣機
What kind of form do you like?
那你是喜歡什麼樣的形式啊
what is quiet or what
什麼安靜的,還是什麼
A lot of descriptions are finished
一大堆描述寫完呢
they recommend you right away
他們馬上幫你推薦
Then this recommendation system does not mean
那這個推薦系統不是說
The manufacturer said his air conditioner is very quiet
那個廠商說他的冷氣機很安靜
I went to many blogs to read
是到很多的部落格去看
Say what these people said about this air conditioner
說這些人對這個冷氣機的評價
collect him all
把他全部收集起來
Then hit a new score
然後再打一個新的分數
so it's very complicated
所以是非常複雜的
this type of ad
這個型廣告
future ads
以後的廣告
We watch a lot of movies on that internet now
我們現在看那個網路上有很多電影
In particular, many serial machines in mainland China have already been installed.
尤其是大陸很多那個連續機都已經放上去
He is not afraid of your computer now
他現在電腦也不怕你看
Because you watch TV and watch commercials
因為你在看電視也要看廣告
The computer also sees advertisements
電腦也是看廣告
So he thinks there is no difference
所以他覺得是沒有差別的
That part of the ad cannot be omitted
那廣告那一段是不能省略
You can't press it no matter what
你怎麼按也按不掉
he kept talking
他就一直講
Now the advertisements are the same as those on TV, everyone sees the same advertisement
現在廣告是跟電視上一樣,所有人看哪個廣告都一樣
If he's smarter in the future, his ad, you've changed seasons recently and want to buy some clothes or your shoes are broken
如果以後他聰明一點,他的廣告,你最近換季了,想要買一些衣服或是鞋子壞了
If he knows, he will put some things you really like, and the style is based on the shoes you bought before for a comparison
他如果知道的話,他就把一些你真的喜歡的東西,而且那個style是根據你以前買的鞋子做一個比對
That ad, you saw it and immediately went out to buy it, or bought it online
那個廣告,你看了馬上就出門去買,或者是上網買
It is very meaningful to recommend
這樣推薦就非常有意義的
Intelligent teaching assistant agent and health system
智慧型助教代理和健康系統
IBM's WATCHEN is to push his entire system to Medical Science
IBM的WATCHEN就是把他的整個系統推到Medical Science上面去
We are now talking about assistant teaching assistants. In fact, we did it a long time ago, but because we are not very smart
我們現在講助教代理人,其實我們很久以前是做過,不過因為不太聰明
So 24 hours is not used by so many people
所以24小時並沒有那麼多人用
Future teaching assistants, we just finished, have to be very smart
以後的助教代理人,我們剛剛講完,要非常聰明
Teaching assistant agent Math assistant agent
助教代理 數學助教代理
If the elementary school mathematics just now
如果剛才那個小學數學
you can get 90 points
你可以考到90分
or 95 points
或者95分
Everyone can be a teaching assistant
大家就可以當助教
but you also need to understand
但你還要了解
There is also a question answering system
還有一個問答系統
Can understand the meaning of questions that students don't understand
可以聽懂學生不懂的問法是什麼意思
can help him explain
可以幫他解釋
I think this is the greatest help for all children
這我覺得對所有小孩的幫助是最大
English and Mathematics
英文和數學
This is medically related
這個是在醫療上有關的
it's big
這是大 啊
the university wrote a
大學寫了一個
A description of a patient's condition
一個病人的情況的描述
Jennifer States
Jennifer States
what we have to do is
我們要做的是
Computer poison to all Risk Factor
電腦毒到所有Risk Factor
remember it
要把它記起來
Then put all the Medication
然後呢 把所有的Medication
he
他
what did the doctor prescribe
醫生開了什麼藥
Or what medicine did he take to remember it
或者他吃過什麼藥把它記起來
Then he went to do the quality of the health check
然後這個他去做健康檢查的這些質
pick him up
把他協采
and put it in this
然後就放在這個裡面
Put it in and he will know
放在裡面他就可以知道
What is Connected Risk Factor
Connected Risk Factor是什麼東西
Medical Lyrical Minds, this business literature is growing very fast. Generally, reading or reading papers in many fields is very important, but not as important as Medical Science
Medical Lyrical Minds,這個生意文獻成長非常快速,一般在很多領域讀書或讀paper是很重要,但沒有像Medical Science那麼重要
Because everyone in Medical Science knows why it screens out and seeks a higher level, because any one of it, such as doing a certain experiment on a veteran, will be of interest to everyone
因為Medical Science各位知道它為什麼篩退尋高,因為它任何一個譬如在老手上做某個實驗,大家都會有興趣
Because it wants to know whether it will have a similar effect if the same experiment is done on humans, so its broadness is very strong
因為它會想說如果在人上面做同樣的實驗是不是有一個類似的效果,所以它的那種廣泛性非常強
You can’t do it in computer science. If you read the paper in your field in the field of computer science, you probably can’t make a mistake. You can’t understand other things if you want to read them.
computer science就不會,computer science十幾二十的領域你就讀你的領域的paper大概就不會錯,其他你要讀也讀不懂
As for this aspect, so Medical Science they often say that I have a problem and I want the computer to help me find it. Now if I use Google, it returns tens of thousands of tablets every time.
那這個方面,所以Medical Science他們常常會說我有一個問題想要電腦去幫我找,現在如果用Google的話它每次回來是上萬片
Generally speaking, when we search on Google, it doesn’t matter if there are tens of thousands of pieces, because the first ten probably have what I want, bye
一般我們講說我們在Google上search,它有上萬片沒有關係,因為前面十個大概就有我要的東西,拜拜
For example, you need to know which genes are related to a certain disease
比如說某一個疾病你要知道他和哪些基因有關係
This may really require hundreds of thousands of papers to read
這個可能真的是要十幾萬篇paper都去讀
Then there are some sentences in him saying that this is very helpful for something
然後他裡面有一些句子說這個對什麼什麼很有幫助
You really have to read every sentence.
真的一句一句都要讀到才有辦法
So the answer to this kind of question is very difficult.
所以這種問題的答案非常難一下讀會
Gene-to-Gene Interactions
基因和基因之間的相互作用
And cancer patients, genetic mutations, and methods of diagnosis and treatment
還有癌症病患 基因變異還有診療方式
People who are sick are very careful
這個他們生病的人都非常care
can you read soon
你是不是很快的可以讀到
These papers related to him
這個跟他相關的這些paper
Also, what the President of the United States is promoting is not presuci medicine
還有美國總統現在推的不是presuci medicine
It's Personalized Medicine
這是一個個人化的醫療
How to collect these data
這些資料怎麼去收集
How to do a comparison with your genes
怎麼跟你的基因做一個比對
It has something to do with the above problems
就跟前面這些問題都有關係
so the answer to any question
所以任何一個問題的回答
It may involve really reading so many papers
可能就牽涉到真正要讀這麼多paper
It is impossible to have this manpower now
那現在是不可能有這個人力
impossible in the future
以後也不可能
So this aspect requires the help of a computer.
所以這一方面就很需要電腦的幫助
So life scientists need a comparison
所以生活學家需要一個比過
has a hundred times more searches
有百倍的搜尋
Here is the end
下面是快到結束了
This has something to do with your work
這跟各位的工作會有關係
What does the next issue have to do with doing things?
下期和做事有什麼關聯
let's talk first
我們首先講
In fact, many things in society are now hierarchically responsible.
現在其實社會上很多事情都是分層負責
because you called the travel agency
因為你打電話到旅行社
Said that I want to go to Pupu Island or Green Island
說我要到普及島或者綠島
Or to Orchid Island
或者到蘭嶼
he has not been to these places
他並沒有去過這些地方
but there are other people beside him
但是他旁邊有其他人
or someone from another company
或者是其他公司的人
He can help you collect information
他就可以幫你收集資訊
tell you what's the fun
跟你說這是什麼好玩
It's up to you to decide whether to go to this place
你來決定要不要去這個地方
When is there a big inspection
什麼時候有大檢價
what temperature
什麼氣溫如何
Many things are in charge of different people
很多東西都是不同的人負責
So each class works
所以每一個階層的工作
data collection
都是資料收集
Decide how the next level of work will be organized
決定下一層的工作如何安排進行
can do it well
就可以把它做好
If all levels make coordinated decisions
如果每一個階層都做好協調決策
Complete work can go smoothly
成底工作可以順利團
that means
這意思就是說
If the following are all robots
如果下面都是機器人
this is all your work left
你的工作就只剩這個
the coordination and decision making
這個協調和做決策
if your job
如果你的工作
You can also use the code name of the machine, you don't need to exist
也可以用機器的代號你就不需要存在
so this is troublesome
所以這個很麻煩
so why is it like playing chess
所以這為什麼跟下棋一樣
Our every decision-making process is very similar to playing chess
我們每一個決策過程跟下棋很像
it's your son
就是這是你下的一子
The opponent may play this one
對方可能下這一子
or go somewhere else
或是下別的地方
So how many steps do you have to consider
那你要考慮的步驟是有多少
It's possible that if he gets down here
就是可能他如果下這裡的話
You go to another place in the second step
你第二步再下另外一個地方
third step
第三步
is the step you have to consider
就是你要考慮的步驟
what's your final decision
你最後決策怎麼下
So it's very similar to playing chess
所以跟下棋是非常像的
If you do this every step
如果你這個每一個步驟
have an agent
都有一個代理人
agent machine talk to you
機器代理人跟你講說
If you take this step
你如果走這個步驟
what is his likely success rate
他的可能成功率是多少
Then such words
那這樣的話
you can make a decision soon
你就很快可以做個決定
But if there are so many machines
但是如果有這麼多機器
your job to decide
你做決定的工作
will be replaced by robots
也會被機器人取代
So it's slowly
所以是慢慢的就是說
we are bottom up
我們是由下而上
OK, parameter setting of the biological laboratory
好 生物實驗室的參數設定
Which combination should be tried first
那一種組合要優先嘗試
that one is the second try
那一個是第二嘗試
You want the computer to make a list
你希望電腦列一個表出來
Then you just have to make a choice
然後你只要做個選擇就好
Then if he has the ability
那如果他有這個能力的話
Maybe one day he'll tell you
那有一天可能他會跟你講說
I've helped you choose the best for this role
我已經幫你選到最好的這個角色
Well, he doesn't need you at all
那其實他根本不需要你
That is to say, in many experiments
就是說在很多實驗上面
If he can automate later
如果他後面可以自動化
Then we really don’t need to do dry lab today
那我們今天做dry lab真的就不需要
Because we told the computer to try it out
因為我們跟電腦說你去試一下
Replace this parameter with that one and run out
這個參數換成那個跑出來
he may have to run for a day or two
他可能要跑一天兩天
If you say this action, the computer will do it
如果說這個動作電腦就會做
He can help you to try different parameters
他可以幫你去試不同參數
If the computer is fast enough
那如果電腦夠快的話
These things can be done right now
這些東西都可以馬上做完
Discussion on research direction
研究方向探討
What method is used which one comes first and which one comes after
用什麼方法是哪一個先哪一個後
depth first
深度優先
Go down in depth first
深度優先就往下走
Breadth first go sideways
廣度優先往旁邊走
Law of success
成功劇律
So now all we need is to say
所以現在我們缺的只是說
Not a single computer can help us anytime soon
沒有一個電腦可以幫我們很快
Calculate these laws of success
把這些成功劇律計算出來
Now in many fields, like in the field of FanX show, they may have it, because he has a lot of data, he can estimate what will happen if you invest in US dollars now
現在很多領域,像在FanX show這個領域,他們可能就有,因為他有很大的數據,他可以估計你如果投資現在投資美金會怎麼樣
The price of the US dollar has risen in the past two days, should I buy it immediately, or buy it in two days, how to do things in Changhua, how to learn
這兩天美金漲價,是不是馬上去買,還是過兩天再買,做事情彰化,如何學論
The same is true for this. Didn’t we talk about text comprehension just now?
這個也是一樣,剛才我們不是有講篇章理解嗎?
This computer learns a lot, he can also write, because those sentences come and go, he can add one, but although he can add everything, there is nothing difficult
這個電腦學多了,他也會寫,因為那些句子來去,他加一個儘管,但是雖然什麼都他都會加,沒有什麼難的
In the future, speeches will be relatively simple, that is, I will write the first few sheets for him to prepare for the exam.
以後演講也比較簡單的,就是前面的幾張都給他去寫,準備考試
As we said earlier, the exam bot is already preparing the email
剛我們講過,考試機器人已經在準備電子郵件
The last one is which jobs are easily replaced by robots, which are low-level agent jobs
最後一張是哪些工作容易被機器人取代,就是低階的代理人工作
So everyone, think about it, if you are about to enter the workplace now, I often tell master students, don't think trivial things
所以各位去思考一下,如果你現在正要投入職場,我常常跟碩士生講,你不要認為小事
high salary now
現在薪水很高
when you turn 40
你到40歲的時候
How much more powerful was the computer than you at that time
那時候電腦比你強多少倍
Many people face this choice at the age of 30 or 40
很多人在30、40歲面臨這個抉擇
Say he wants to change the line
說他要不要換行
Because of his line of work, he is already weaker than the newcomers
因為他這一行他已經比剛來的人要弱
Now it is compared with people and later it will be compared with computers
現在是跟人比以後是跟電腦比
The work content is simple and repetitive
工作內容單純重複性高
like a factory without lights
譬如無燈工廠
I don't need anyone anymore
已經不需要人了
simple customer service questions
簡單的客服問題
read simple script
讀簡單的寫字化的
These DTLs are quick to do
這些DTL很快就可以做
The most complex part of every job is still handled by someone
每項工作中最複雜的部分還是有人處理
But there are fewer and fewer people to hire
但需要僱用的人越來越少
we just said
剛才我們講過
For example, there may only be 20% of difficult questions in customer service questions
像客服問題裡面可能只有20%的困難問題
need real people to answer
需要真的人去回答
But other words don't need
但其他的話就不需要
So like now many banks have more than 200 customer service
所以像現在很多銀行過200個客服
in a few years
過個幾年
We are now going to help banks build an automated answering system
我們現在就要幫銀行做自動回答系統
After a few years, he may only need 50, 20 customer service
過了幾年他可能只需要50個、20個客服
real people are answering
真的人在回答
Because simple problems are already
因為簡單的問題都已經
What Google Designs Now
Google現在設計的信仰
Because Google says you type in a question
因為Google說你一個問題打進去
It answers in 0.4 seconds after writing on it
它上面寫0.4秒就回答完
In fact, your question has already been asked
其實你的問題都有人問過了
It only needs to search in front of that
它只要到那個前面去搜
How did you shoot this question?
這個問過的是怎麼拍的
It doesn't need to re-find it for you
它根本不需要的重新幫你找
So 90% of the questions are already asked
所以90%的問題都是有人問過的
That's what we call an FAQ
那個就是我們所謂的常問問題
no need to search anymore
都不需要再去搜索
The most complex part of every job needs you to deal with
每項工作最複雜部分需要你處理
But if this complexity
但是如果這種複雜度
What kind of complexity are we looking at
我們要看什麼樣的複雜度
If its complexity is only because it has too many possibilities
如果它的複雜度只是因為它可能性太多
Or you have trouble explaining to it
或者你要跟它交代起來很麻煩
might as well do it yourself
還不如自己做
In this way, the computer in the future will be faster
這樣的話比較以後的電腦變快
like we just said
像我們剛剛講說
You have to run for a day or two with any set of parameters
你隨便一組參數要跑一兩天
In the future, the computer may run out for a minute or two
以後電腦可能跑了一兩分鐘就跑出來
this is no joke
這個不是開玩笑
It's very likely a minute or two to run out
這是非常可能一兩分鐘跑出來
You can quickly think, you help me run these 100 kinds of parameter groups
你就可以很快想,你幫我跑這100種參數組
Then, after he understands your words, he will run away by himself in the future
那你這句話,他聽懂了以後,他以後自己就會去跑
He doesn't need you, if he is more considerate, everyone can gradually automate these
他不需要你,更善解人意的話,這些大家都可以逐步自動化
So if what a master student does is to try out different possibilities
所以如果說一個碩士生做的事情,就是去試不同的可能性
But the teacher will tell him a direction, which is more difficult
但老師會跟他講一個方向,這個方向是比較難的
But if the computer can understand this direction, then the necessity of this master's existence will also be reduced
但是這個方向如果電腦聽得懂,那這個碩士生存在的必要性也會降低
So in the end machines will replace people faster and faster
所以最後機具取代人士會越來越快
Below what we just talked about, he ran up from that button
我們剛剛講的下面,他從那個button一直往上跑
What we are seeing now is the manufacturing industry, they are talking about one case at a time
我們現在看到的是製造業,他們現在講一例一休
The implementation started last year, and many factories immediately bought more than 1,000 robots
去年就開始實施,很多工廠馬上就買了1000多台機器人
Because the degree of automation in the manufacturing industry is already very high
因為在製造業上面的這種自動化程度已經很高
Now it's the same in the office
現在是在辦公室也是一樣
If our secretary asks for too much leave every day, he will take this
如果每天我們這個秘書請假太多,他就會把這個
This secretary machine has been introduced
這個秘書機器已經引進了
Ingredient designer if moody day and night
成分設計師如果一天天晚上鬧情緒
Low-level composition design is completely done by computer
低階的成分設計就完全有電腦做
24 hours is scary
24小時很可怕
and he's very fast
而且他速度非常快
simple assistant
簡單助理
This is a teacher I just talked about
這個是一個教師就是我剛講
Also watch out
也要Watch out
Because there are so many good teaching materials on the Internet
因為現在網路上非常多很好的教材
are taught by very famous teachers.
都是非常有名的老師教的
The only inconvenience is when you say you don't understand
唯一不方便是說你聽不懂的時候
he won't tell you
他不會告訴你
If he had a teacher today with a question answering system next to
如果他今天有一個教師旁邊有一個問答系統
a teaching assistant
一個助教
You don't understand, stop him and ask the teaching assistant
你不懂是把他停下來問一下助教
what did that sentence mean
剛才那句話什麼意思
words he understands
他聽得懂的話
Does this person still need to go to school?
那這個人還需要到學校去學嗎
The best teacher in the world has been recorded
全世界最好的老師已經錄好
The best teaching assistants are by your side to help you answer questions
最好的助教在旁邊幫你回答問題
In this case
這樣的話
many teachers work
很多老師的工作
Like teaching elementary school books, if you have to talk about it, you don’t have to teach it.
像教小學書有講就可以不用教了
because you can only teach one hour a day
因為你只能一天教一小時
That computer is available 24 hours a day
那個電腦一天二十四小時都可以交
no way to compare with him
沒辦法跟他比
so it's very dangerous
所以這是非常危險的
assistant too
助理也是一樣
I'm talking about research assistants
我講的是研究助理
A lot of things for research assistants are highly repetitive
研究助理很多事情是重複性很高的
the more this kind of thing
那越是這種事情
you have to be more careful
你要越要小心
I can write a sincere story later
以後我可以寫一個誠事
Please write a sincere story and replace yourself
請你寫一個誠事把你自己replace掉
This is actually happening
這個事實上已經在發生
no one did it on purpose
不是任何人故意的
that is
就是說
Because what he does is too monotonous
因為他做的事情太單調
He doesn't like doing it either, right?
他也不喜歡做對不對
Then he will write a truth instead
那他就會寫一個誠事來替代
So slowly these jobs will be replaced by machines
所以慢慢的這些工作都會被機器取代
That's all for today's speech
那我今天的這個演講就到這裡為止
thank you
謝謝各位
Thank you, Director Xu, for your wonderful speech.
謝謝許所長非常精采的演講
so we probably still have some time to come
所以我們大概還有一些時間來
Let everyone be open to ask questions
讓大家開放問問題
good here
好這邊
Press the front microphone
按前面麥克風
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
好謝謝老師精采的演講
I am interested and want to ask more
我有興趣然後想要多請教
It lies in the Principle-based approach mentioned by the teacher just now
在於剛剛老師提到的Principle-based approach
But like, for example, I just gave a few examples
可是像比方說剛剛舉了幾個例子
It seems to be a bunch of similar things
好像就是說一堆類似的東西裡面
Actively seek out a Principle
積極去找出一個Principle
and make things faster and better
然後讓事情都變得更快更好
But I remember the Mathematics Institute of Academia Sinica
可是我記得中研院的那個數學所
The Journal of Mathematical Communication has been talking about one thing for a while now
數學傳播雜誌有一段時間一直在談一件事
That is to say, the Western period
就是說下西洋期
It seems to be able to notice that there is a similarity with arithmetic
它好像可以注意到跟算數學有一個類似的地方
It's the spirit of learning mathematics
就是學數學學的越精神
People who go up and down are better
下起下的越好的人
The more he seems to be able to raise his point of view
他好像越能夠提高觀點看事情
So the teacher's Principle-based approach
所以老師的Principle-based approach
When the computer formulates these Principles
電腦在制定這些Principle的時候
Is there any way for him to raise or lower his level
他有沒有辦法去提高層次或降低層次
In other words, is there a way for him to say
換言之他有沒有辦法就是說
From only being able to see whether the reference is right or wrong
從只能夠看reference對或錯
into a paper
變成看一篇論文裡面
Does he lack Principle
他是不是有缺少Principle
Or is there a way for him to
或者是說他有沒有辦法從
I know a person makes a typo in a sentence
知道一個人一句話裡面講錯字
Become a person who knows that he will not look at the four lines and say the wrong thing
變成知道一個人他不會看四行場合講錯話
So your Principals are all parallel?
所以您的Principal是全部都平行的嗎?
Or can he see the Principals of different classes from top to bottom?
還是說他可以看出上下不同階層的Principal
This question is very knowledgeable
這問題問得很有學問
It's just that some people may not hear clearly
就是可能有些人聽不太清楚
That is to say, when you study, you acquire the superficial knowledge.
就是說你學的時候你是學到表面的這個知識
Or you can learn more abstract
還是你可以學到更抽象的
In fact, computers need to learn abstract knowledge
其實電腦要學抽象知識
not difficult
不難
because of U.S
因為我們
especially since we've done a lot of this kind of speech analysis
尤其在我們所已經做過很多這種語音分析
So every word has its upper position
所以每一個詞它都有它的上位
more superior
更上位
like that
像那個
Banana right?
香蕉對不對
it is a fruit
它是一個水果
Another what to eat
又是一個什麼可吃的什麼
then we are all done
那我們都已經做好
so
所以
Today I learned a Pattern
今天我學到一個Pattern
I can ginarize it to a higher level immediately
我馬上可以把它ginarize到一個比較高的境界
not its original word
不是它原來的詞
that this
那這個
In this relatively high Pattern
在這個比較高的Pattern裡面
fits a lot
符合的就非常多
At this time, it is equivalent to saying
這個時候等於說
I can use it elsewhere
我就可以用到別的地方
so next time you put this
所以你下次把這個
There will be no problem changing orange apple
orange apple換一換都不會有問題
This is absolutely no problem
這個是絕對沒有問題的
Thanks
謝謝
ok there's someone over there
好 那邊有一位
Want to know more about that
想要了解一下就是那個
PBA seems to be able to understand some semantics
PBA看起來就是可以去了解一些語意
green
綠色的
That is, PBA seems to understand some semantics
就是PBA看起來可以了解一些語意
Is it possible that it produces
那它有沒有可能就是產生
that is to say the writing part
就是說寫的部分
Use the PBA way to generate some of that
用PBA的方式去產生一些那個
that's easy because
那很簡單 因為
you think it's the other way around
你想的這是一個反過來
I just didn't give an example to say
就是當初我不是舉個例子說
How would you describe the distance between two points
你要怎麼描述兩個點的距離
Is the distance between the two places correct?
兩個地方的距離對不對
Then you collect such tools
那你收集這麼具
next time i ask you to talk
下次我要你講的時候
you take one of you
你就把你中間某一個
Pick it out and talk it out and it's over
挑出來講出去就結束了
So its absorption and production are the same thing
所以它的吸收和產生是同一回事
the same thing
同一回事
Then its sentence pattern means
那它句型就是說
I change it here
我在這個地方把它換
what is this noun
這個名詞換成什麼
What is that noun replaced with?
那個名詞換成什麼
it can have another meaning
它就可以產生另外一個意思
this too
這個也是
You can go backwards from the process of learning it
都可以從它在學的過程就倒退回去
still have a question
還有一個問題
that joke
那個笑調
That's the one
就是那個
like in Chinese
像以中文來講的話
Just use the PBI method
就是用PBI這個方法的話
Approximately how many Principals are there?
大概有多少個Principal
Can let the machine understand Chinese
可以讓機器去了解中文
what about other languages
那其他語言呢
this really needs to be understood
這個真的要了解
Because there are so many Principals
因為那Principal非常多
speak like we do
像我們這樣講
when we were checking restaurants
我們在查餐廳的時候
will anyone speak
有任何人會講說
I have a friend
我有一個朋友
like to drink
喜歡喝酒
which restaurant is suitable
哪一個餐廳合適
he talked for a long time
他講了半天
just looking for a place to drink
就是要找一個地方可以喝酒
If you need to understand this sentence
這句話要了解的話
how many different ways
有多少不同的講法
Can be mapped to
可以Map到
can like to drink
可以喜歡喝酒
this is
這個就是
Benefits of Big Data
大數據的好處
I can be online today
今天我可以在網路上
collect a lot of sentences like these
收集很多這些類似的句子
i know i like to drink
我就知道說喜歡喝酒
How many different ways are there
大概有多少不同的講法
I can filter it out
我可以把它篩選出來
i am this one
我是這一個
Map
Map
You can't do that with Dibnurin
這你沒有辦法用Dibnurin做
Because the expression of so-called meaning is human assign
因為所謂意義的表達都是人assign
There is no saving energy on this aspect.
這一方面是省不掉力氣的
But you only need to collect this information
但是你只要收集到這個資料過來
Our principle can be learned immediately
我們的principle馬上就可以學起來
I don't know if this answers your question
我不知道這是不是回答你的問題
I can explain it with PPA
我好解釋就是用PPA的話
The complexity is similar across languages
在不同語言上的複雜度是類似的
Its PPA has nothing to do with the language
它這個PPA是跟語言沒有關系
is your grammar or something
就是你的文法什麼東西
Your pattern itself already contains
你的pattern本身就已經包含了
so it doesn't matter how your grammar is
所以它並不關你文法怎麼樣
It can even learn your grammar
它甚至於可以把你的文法都學出來
For example, English verb singular plus S something
比如是英文的動詞單數加S什麼東西
It can learn those things by itself
那些東西它自己都可以學出來
So it has the benefit of that law
所以它有那個法則式的好處
It also has statistical calculation capabilities for this type of insertion deletion
它也有統計式的這種insertion deletion的計算能力
ok, the gentleman in the back
好 後面那位先生
Teacher Qiu
邱老師
Just now you mentioned that
剛剛您有提到說
People are talking about many conditions in the province
人在講話省內的很多條件
right
對
people in different situations
就是人在不同的情境裡面
He can understand what you mean by planning
他可以理解說你是計畫什麼意思
But in the opposite direction, you can tell the machine to write a novel
但反方向可以叫機器寫小說
he is equivalent to
他相當於
because people have imagination
因為人有想像
Then he can also imagine many conditions
那他也可以想像好多條件
like when the teacher mentioned
像老師提的時候
Taipei Taichung
台北台中
In front he is selling tickets
在前面他是賣票
you want to buy a ticket
你要買票
But just write Taipei Taichung
但只要寫台北台中
This machine can imagine
這機器就可以想像
what's in taipei
台北有什麼
what's in taichung
台中有什麼
Immediately afterwards he wrote a novel
之後他馬上寫一篇小說
He went to Taipei to Taichung to play
他到台北到台中去玩
meet someone
遇到什麼人
who are you in love with
又跟誰戀愛
a lot of them all come out
一大堆全部都出來
Is it possible to write a novel
那是不是可以寫小說
He inversely creates situations for himself
他反方向自己製造情境
we talked about this
這個東西我們講過
that is
就是說
You just have to teach him something
你只要給他學什麼東西
he can have a similar effect
他就可以產生類似的效果
this is possible
這是可能的
if you give him a lot of this novel
如果你給他很多這一段小說
he will read love novels
他就會去看愛情小說
different from the other one, what happened first and what happened later
跟另外一個不同,先發生什麼再發生什麼
After he remembers these things
他把這些東西要記起來以後
He has another Principle Base to remember these
他又有一個Principle Base去把這些記起來
Then things with similarities and minor differences will be regenerated by him.
然後大同小異的東西都會被他再產生出來
For example, when we write a letter of introduction
譬如說我們在寫介紹信的時候
We usually say that the student is very hardworking
我們通常會說這個學生非常用功
But he's not the smartest, we don't speak negatively
但是他不是最聰明,我們不會用否定的話講
we will turn around, right?
我們會轉折對不對
From work to business, I talked for a long time
這個工作到生意,講了半天
You can tell that he's not that smart
你可以看得出來,說他不是這麼聰明
In this sentence, this sequence can be handed over to the computer
這句話,這個sequence可以交給電腦之後
you mark a lot of paragraphs like this
你就標很多這樣的段落
Tell him that's a description that says he's hardworking, but not the smartest
跟他說這是描述說很用功,但不是最聰明
5 percent, 10 percent, 20 percent than what we marked
比我們標百分之五百分之十,百分之二十那種東西
He'll learn how to talk about five percent in the future
他以後就會學說怎麼去講百分之五的
How do you say twenty percent ten percent
怎麼講百分之二十的百分之十的
so this is possible
所以這個都是可能
But the front needs people to meet this standard
但是前面需要人去做這個標準
if he has the ability
如果他有這麼能力的話
right
對
assume an architect
假設一個建築師
Others have a piece of land
他人家有一塊地
the style he wants to cover
他要蓋的那個style
almost a thousand kinds
幾乎是千百種
that in this case
那在這種情況下
Can the machine also
機器是不是也可以
lots of imagination
很多想像力
I use this pattern to give him
我用這個pattern給他
build this
建這個
what flavor is he
他是什麼風味
what personality does he fit
他吻合什麼個性
he almost
他幾乎就
let the architect to some extent
讓建築師某個程度
He said you design 100
他就說你設計100個
Then when he picked the third
之後他挑第三個的時候
actually i think
其實我覺得
you are right
您講的沒有錯
today we
今天我們
machine can't do
機器不能做
It's because we humans don't know how to teach him
是因為我們人不會教他
because we're kind of like
因為我們有點像
Teach a cram student
教一個補習班學生
only one inside
裡面只有一個
is the computer
就是電腦
if i could teach
我如果會教的話
his ability to abstract
他那個抽象能力
will be very strong
會非常強
so because
所以是因為
i won't abstract the way
我不會抽象的方式
to teach this student
來教這個學生
So he has no way to generalize
所以他沒有辦法generalize
if i will
如果我會的話
Actually this
其實這個
you want him to generalize
你要他generalize
like i think say
像我覺得說
popular songs now
現在流行歌曲
listen carefully
你仔細去聽
his kind though
他那種雖然
not exactly the same
不是完全一樣
but very heavy
但是非常重
There are several inflections
這中間有幾個變調
If the computer memorizes this pattern
如果說電腦把這種pattern背起來的話
it will write a similar
它會寫一個類似的
especially when we talk about
尤其是我們現在講
Said that there are many dance songs in Korea that are well written
說韓國有很多跳舞的歌曲寫得不錯
Then I learn a bit and I can make one myself
那我學一下我就可以自己做一個
And it's guaranteed to be different
而且保證跟它不一樣
no way to sue me
沒辦法告我的
So things like this are possible in the future
所以這一類東西在以後都可能
just say now
只是說現在
the hard part is saying
難的地方是說
We haven't caught that expression yet.
那個表達的方式我們還沒抓到
if caught
如果抓到的話
It will be much easier than image recognition
它這個會比影像辨識要容易很多
ok over there thanks
好,那邊謝謝
very good speech
非常精彩的演講
I bought a book about this two years ago
這個我差不多兩年前去買了一本書
called "how to speed"
叫《如何速度》
not line by line
不是用一行一行的
speed
速度
I read half of the book and still don't understand
我看了半本還不懂
Later I understood that you are looking for the pattern
後來我懂了就是你去找pattern
right
對
right? just say
對不對,你就說
It gives you a square and you go find the pattern
它給你一個方塊你去找pattern
That's because you already have some
那因為你腦子裡面已經有一些
So you know what it means when you see those words
所以你看到那几个字就知道那个意思
This is a bit like what you just said
这个有点像你刚才所说的
Your reference is to use one dimensional
你的那个reference是用one dimensional
is a series
就是一系列的
Now it's impossible to read this like you said
现在可不可能就像你说读这个
business book like
生意的书一样
Also go to find the pattern in this text
也去在这个文字中去找pattern
So it's like saying look at everyone
那因此就像说你看大家小的
This Chinese has a former dean named Sony Chen
这个中文就有一个以前有一个院长叫Sony Chen
It doesn't matter if he goes to bed at 3 o'clock all day and half sleeps
他整天天晚三点点睡觉睡一半都没有关系
but he asks questions
但是他会问问题
I think he also found a pattern
我觉得他也是找到pattern
is he knows him
就是他知道他
Halfway through your talk, he already knows about other things.
你讲一半他就已经知道大概其他的事什么了
So he has already decided the question
因此他就已经决定了这个问题了
So in general, this is the pattern
所以说来说去就是这个pattern
Will not become two dimensional
可不会变成two dimensional
To become something else is for him to sporadically find out some
变成另外的就是他sporadically来找出一些
law
規律
Is this right with Xiaoxiang?
那這是不是跟小相立
In fact, part of
其實就是有一部分是
This is actually
這個其實
With the basic ability of the computer
電腦的基本能力有了以後
to make this change
要做這種變化
it's very easy to tell him
對他講是非常容易的
The difference now is that the understanding of basic things is not enough
現在差在基本的東西理解力還不夠
So I'm assuming he's improving so fast
所以我就是他進步的程度會飛快
He will improve by leaps and bounds after reaching a level
他到了一個level以後會突飛猛進
so you said
所以您講的
write a story what?
寫故事啊什麼東西
are very likely
都是非常有可能
And there will be quite a bit of exclusivity
而且獨家會相當有
Tasteful experience
經歷有味
that is
就是說
not casually
不是隨便
good over there
好那邊
To tell you the truth, I'm also an information
說實在我也是搞資訊的
But learn for you on the screen
但是在畫面給你學習
No no
沒有沒有
I feel like
我現在覺得就是
Because of the problem just mentioned
因為剛剛講的問題
is his relevance
就是他的關聯性
Then we put it from the original system
然後我們把它原來從系統裡面
You do regular system analysis first
你先做常做系統分析
analysis becomes structure
分析變成結構
The structure will later become Majiu and become a block
結構以後變成麻酒變成區塊
right
對
slowly become
慢慢就變成
he will become a parameter
他會變成一個參數
On the top
最上面
A parameter structure has
一個參數 結構都有了
Now the other sea and air joint defense is our anti-fat gallbladder
那現在另外海空聯防的就是我們防肥膽
That is the whole from the satellite to the bottom
那個是整個從衛星到下面
is also an enterprise architecture
也是一個企業架構
Enterprise Architecture
Enterprise Architecture
It is also doing the whole structure integration
也是在做整個架構整合
That architecture has reasoning
那個架構都有推理
Now I'm doing something with some friends
那我現在跟幾個朋友在做一件事情
that is
就是說
In this way, some parts may need to be consulted with you
用這個方式可能有部分要跟您請教
can help
可以幫得上
at this
在這個
We can wait for this and we are off the market
這個我們可以等一下我們下市
It's okay, I just said something
沒有關係 我剛剛講一下
It's on the Buddhist scriptures
就是在佛經上面
It's just too complicated, repetitive scenes and characters appear
就是太複雜 重複的場景跟人物出現
In fact, several parameters are extracted from it.
其實裡面萃取出來都幾個參數在裡面
over here
那這邊
structure we already have
結構我們已經有了
Then these screened parts
那後面這些篩選的部分
and for example
還有比如說
More than 100 Buddhist medium personalities
100多個佛媒個性
Then each individual element
然後每個個性的元素
I'll ask you later
到時候再給您請教
can you use this to help
可以不可以用這個來幫忙
So this is how to refine Buddhist scriptures into
那這是如何把佛經收煉成
For example, it is a copy of Uncle Si
跟比如說四叔是一本
a bible ist
聖經ist一本
can refine him
可以把他收煉起來
Ben has been good for so many years
班這麼多年發善
everyone speak one
每一個人講一個
You explain me and I don't understand until now
你解釋我解釋到現在不清楚
In fact, it is found that the structure is quite clear
其實發現結構滿清楚的
that time here
那這邊到時候
it's absolutely possible
這絕對可能
right now we
我們現在
One of the things they did to help the food and clothing store was to put
在幫那個食衣所他們做的一件事就是說把
Earlier
以前的
What is that twenty forty?
那個二十四十什麼東西
All these people, officials and civilians inside, what?
裡面的所有的這些人民啊官民啊什麼
find all the horizon
地平全部找出來
and then with the current location
然後跟現在的地點
GPS corresponds to it
GPS把它給對應起來
There is one of these things
這些東西都是有一個
pretty solid result
蠻固定的結果
So it means
所以意思就是說
as long as you will take him
只要你會帶他
After you tell him some important notes
你把一些重要的標註告訴他以後
have enough of
有足夠的
data he can learn
data他就可以學會
After learning it, he can make this mark instead of you
學會以後他就可以代替你做這個標註
In this way, your understanding of the article will be more and more marked
這樣的話你那個文章的理解程度就越來越多的標註
for you to understand
可以供你去理解的
that paragraph of the article
那個那一段文章的話
This story is easier to present
這個story就比較容易呈現出來
so
所以
just said
剛才講的說
There is his little story in one sentence
一個句子裡面有他的小的story
sentence like a small sentence paragraph
句子像個小的話句一段
There is more in a paragraph
一段話裡面有比較更
But it's actually the way it starts and turns
但是其實是它的那個起程轉合的方式
can be learned
都是可以學得到
the same book
那一本書也是一樣
Here's a gentleman after
這邊有一位先生之後
we probably don't have much time
我們大概沒有太多時間
Good idea, the question I want to ask is relatively basic
主張好,我想請問的問題是比較基本的
implementation part
implementation的部分
Just now you mentioned that you need to mark
剛剛您提到有要標註
that's there
那在
The current mainstream trust understanding
目前比較主流的信任領會
in you
在您裡面
it may be used
它可能是用
Word to vet is to quantify these words
word to vet,就是將這些文字相量化
Including these principles
包括這些principle
Possibly also with phasors
可能也用相量
Then use some probability parameters
再用一些機率的參數
is it here
在這邊是不是
This imbedding or this
這個imbedding或者是這個
Is there a label
標註是不是也有
use this method
用這個方法
this thing is very useful
這個東西是很好用
but it is important to understand
但是它對理解
It actually does that kind of cluster
它其實是做那種cluster
its comprehension comparison to those who understand
它對理解的人的理解比較
Not helpful, but he does a lot of tools that are very useful
沒有幫助,但是他做很多工具是非常好用
We now hope to have a new world full factor
我們現在希望能夠有一個新的world full factor
understandable
是人看得懂的
It is also a vector, a vector that people can understand
也是一個vector,人看得懂的一個vector
Then he has the same effect
然後他有同樣的效果
In this way, it can replace a vector that is now purely quantitative
這樣的話就是能夠取代那個現在純粹是數量的一個vector
Then when he learns, his skills will be stronger
那這樣他學習的時候那個功力就會更強
Then he marked it manually, Nano or machine learning
那他這個標註是用人工,Nano還是用機器學標註
is the algorithm
就是演算法
It's half manual and half learned.
這個都是一半人工一半學的
All have to be learned automatically, it is impossible to rely on people
都是要自動學,不可能全部靠人
Excuse me
請問一下
just heard you say that
剛剛聽你這樣講
That is to say, let the so-called computer deal with the dead.
就是說這個要讓所謂的電腦去處理死人的事情
is getting easier
是越來越容易
The problem is that if you turn the living into the dead
那問題是如果把活人變成死人
According to your rigid method there should be a
依照你的僵硬法應該有一個
A very basic database
一個很基本的一個database
For example, the correspondence of words
那例如說文字的對應
There are so-called Chinese characters in the oriental characters
在東方的字裡面有所謂的漢字
There are new Chinese characters
還有新漢字
even privately printed Chinese characters
甚至以私印漢字
If you say these
那如果說這些
In the latest privately printed Chinese characters
以最新的私印漢字來
So if it is in the information system of the China Theater Academy
所如果說在中演院裡面的資訊系統裡面
because of the word
因為這一個字
This so-called privately printed Chinese character is illiterate
這一個所謂的私印漢字是文盲的話
Then all the expressions using privately printed Chinese characters
那所有的使用私印漢字的表達
the living
的這些活人
can never be
永遠就不可能被
so-called information system
所謂的資訊系統
replace the dead aspect of the living
把活人的死人的面向取代掉
Is it this way
是不是這樣
Now this is a
現在這個是一個
no shit problem
無所屎的問題
That means we can do one thing today
就是說我們今天能夠做一件事情
Because its influence is greater than one degree
因為它的影響力大到一個程度以上
Whether in academia or industry, we will be able to
才會能不管是在學界或者工業
get enough money to do
拿到足夠的經費來做
so now say
所以現在就是說
any question
任何一個問題
Is it really that influential?
它到底是不是有這麼大影響力
this is more important
這個比較重要
instead of saying this question
而不是說這個問題
does it make sense to some people
是不是對某些人有意義
In fact, when we studied
事實上我們研究的時候
In fact, we have many directions
我們的方向其實有很多種
So we ended up looking for a more capable
所以我們最後都找一個比較能夠
There are funds and someone is willing to do it
有經費 有人願意做
like a lot of things you have money for
像很多事情你有經費
like can't find anyone to do
像找不到人做
Basically not easy to succeed
基本上都不太容易成功
So this is a difficult place
所以這個是一個困難的地方
i think i'll ask
我想那我來問
last question
最後一個問題
Because of something you just said
因為剛剛您說的一些東西
There is something to learn first
都是有一些先學習
because there is some learning
因為是有一些 learning
merge it first
先再把它交匯
so where it starts
所以它開始的地方
is a very well defined
就是一個很 well defined
a path
一個 path
because you already told him
因為你已經告訴他
I'm going this way
我要這樣走了
we are many
我們很多
I think human speaking
我想人類來講
There is a great
這個智慧上有一個很大的
very special one
很特殊的一個
A key point is that people have the ability to create
一個關鍵地方就是人有創造的能力
That is to say, many of us are in the middle of the development of our science
就是說我們很多在我們講Science的發展中間
There are some paradigms
有一些paradigm
is that it is a jump
就是它是一個跳的
something new comes out
一個東西新的出來
and then create a new field
然後開創一個新的領域
so in this regard
所以在這個方面
It is the kind of creative we have now
就是我們現在這種creative的這種東西
Among the students, we often want to find
我們在學生裡都常常要想要找
something
有的東西
Now everyone is talking behind their backs
現在還在大家在底背說
This thing can be learned
這個東西是可以學習來的
or are you born
還是你是天生的
or what about your brain
或者你的腦子特別怎麼樣
so in this regard
所以在這個方面
Is it in the AI
有沒有在AI裡頭
Is there any research going on in this direction
有沒有任何的研究是在走這個方面
This is now because its level is too high
這個現在因為它的層次太高了
That is to say, even if someone has researched
就是說即使有人有研究
I don't care about writing paper
也不管寫paper
because this is written
因為這個寫出來
debateable
debateable
That is, many people will argue
就是很多人會argue
disagree with it
跟它有不同意見
i think there must be
我想一定是有
Like us I remember in the field of mathematics
像我們我記得在數學這個領域
I see many examples
我就看到很多例子
What is set algebra in mathematics?
數學裡面有集合代數什麼東西
He made some new discoveries , important prize - winning discoveries
他有些新的發現,重要的得獎的發現
It was he who brought some concept of geometry to that algebra
是他把幾何的一個什麼概念帶到那個代數去
so he became famous
所以他就變成很有名
abstract substitution
這種抽象式的代換
We just had a gentleman ask
就是我們剛才有一位先生問
Say you see one sentence and think of another
說你看到一個句子會不會想到另外一個
If that correspondence
如果說那種對應
Abstraction corresponds to the words you can rendezvous on the computer
抽象對應你可以把電腦交會的話
he can try
他就可以去試
Some of them might succeed when he tries.
他試的時候可能有些就成功了
So in fact they have someone running an experiment right now
所以事實上他們現在就有人在做一個試驗
That is to say, he asked the computer to prove it.
就是說他讓電腦去做證明
But he simply let the computer generate such abstract things at will
但是他根本就讓電腦隨意產生這種抽象化的事情
See if he can put him in the same way
看他可不可以把他同一個方法
It can be used in different places to prove some new theorems
用在不同地方可以把他證出一些新的定理
This theorem has never been proven
這定理是人以前證不出來的
This kind of experiment is being done
這個有這種實驗在做
So maybe what you're talking about is a bit like
所以可能跟你講的有點像
Then I would like to say that there is another question that is more related to daily life.
那我講還有一個比較日常上比較有關的問題
That is to say we are now online
就是說我們現在上網
search or something
搜尋或什麼
or inside your outer Broadder
或在你的外Broadder裡面
There is inside the browser
有瀏覽器裡面
i have a feeling say
我有一個感覺說
i do everything now
我現在做所有事情
May be Google
可能都被Google
or what is collecting this information
或被什麼在搜集這些資訊
So it means that he is learning to say
所以等於說他在學習說
i will do something
我會做一些什麼事
collect this information
搜集這些資料
then analyze
然後再分析
Then I often find
然後我常常會發現
how to jump out of an ad
怎麼跳出來一個廣告
It seems to be aimed at
好像就是好像針對的
This is a personalized ad
這是個人化的廣告
a reaction of
的一個反應
Now this thing is really going on
現在這個東西是真的在進行
or do we know
還是說我們知道
what the hell is he doing
他到底在做什麼
none of us know
我們都不知道
We are practically all in every move
我們實際上是所有的一舉一動
There is a machine learning
都是有一個機器在學習
he wants to study later
他想要學習以後
he wants to do something
他想要做一些事情
This is actually in progress
這個實際上是在進行中準
this is so
這個是這樣
that is
就是說
It is very strictly managed in Google
Google裡面它管理很嚴格
That is to say, like our machine temple
就是說像我們的機廟
Many of the letters we wrote are in it
我們寫的很多信都在裡面
So it is absolutely not allowed to see
所以它絕對不准人去看
but you can use a computer
但是你可以用電腦
program to read
寫程式去讀
gentlemen
先生
To analyze, people can't see
去分析啊 人不能去看
When is this information more dangerous?
那這個資料什麼時候比較危險
One day the U.S. government
就是有一天美國政府
Trump went up and he said
川普上去 他就說
You give me all this personal information
你把這個某個人資料全部給我
then you have to give
那你非給不行
They are now the US government can go
他們現在美國政府就是可以去
Ask his company for everything
跟他的公司要所有的東西
Then how do you use this thing after you get it?
那這個東西拿來以後怎麼用啊
then we don't know
那我們都不知道
So he will rely on this information in the future
所以他以後靠這些資訊
there are so many things to do
可以做的事情非常多
As for the person in the ad
至於說那個廣告個人的話
this is always done
這個是一直都在做
because it actually does no harm to the user
因為這其實對使用者沒有什麼害處
So those of us Gmail stuff
所以說我們這些Gmail的東西
Humans can't read but machines can
人不能去讀 可是機器可以去讀
So there are so many in the world
所以全世界這麼多的
When he read it, he didn't say
他讀的時候比較不是說
For you personally, but read a general pattern
為你個人 而是讀到一個general的pattern
to the general pattern
對 general pattern
he is not reading personal
他不是讀個人
OK, let's do it today
好 那我們今天就
It ends here
到此結束
thanks again
我們再一次謝謝
Xu said such a brilliant speech
徐說長這麼精采的演講